<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">
  <channel>
    <title>Articles in Citizen Matters categorized under Environment</title>
    <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in</link>
    <atom:link href="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/rss/212507683bc07aea91079rc86caf7cf1f142691a303017" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <description>These are the published articles in Citizen Matters categorized under Environment</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <item>
      <title>Finding the hidden birds in urban green spaces</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/finding-the-hidden-birds-in-urban-green-spaces</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/finding-the-hidden-birds-in-urban-green-spaces</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 02:57:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Deepa Mohan</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/17052/small_birds7.jpg" /><br/><p>Walks are a great way to explore the hidden treasures in the city. This walk in Lalbagh explored many birds and caught them on camera.</p>]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/17052/small_birds7.jpg" /><p id="docs-internal-guid-ba6aea46-b695-dd61-6b2e-22691beb4490" dir="ltr">I was requested by Irina Ghose and Gopal Swaminathan to conduct a nature/birding walk at Lalbagh for their daughter Divya, who was celebrating her birthday.</p>
<p dir="ltr">We gathered most of the group together for a "landmark" shot:</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17046/pic_article_birds1.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">And off we went.</p>
<p dir="ltr">We started with the commonest of birds, the Blue Rock Pigeon:</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17047/pic_article_birds2.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">And the Black Kite (here, a silhouette in the sky):</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17048/pic_article_birds3.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">At the lake, we saw a Little Egret and a Purple Heron:</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17049/pic_article_birds4.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">A Purple Swamphen:</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17050/pic_article_birds5.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">A Common Moorhen:</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17051/pic_article_birds6.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">A White-throated Kingfisher looked out over the rose garden.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17052/pic_article_birds7.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">The Spotted Owlets didn't seem too enthused to see me back again with another group:</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17054/pic_article_birds8.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">It was very nice to see several of the children jotting down the birds' names:</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17055/pic_article_birds9.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">The birds were not the only beautiful things around! This flower is from the Lafoensia vandellina, which is&nbsp;a heritage tree of Lalbagh. <a href="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/print/2173-education-environment-green-spaces-wildlife-children-leisure-the-second-sunday-bngbirds-outing-at-lalbagh" target="_blank">Here</a> is another post I made about this tree.<br /><br /><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17056/pic_article_birds10.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">Some of the historic structures in the park also seemed lost in green dreams of long ago:</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17057/pic_article_birds11.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">In the middle of the cultivated gardens I did find some tiny, exquisite wildflowers.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17058/pic_article_birds12.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>Here's everyone at the end of the walk, they seemed to have had a good time!<br /><br /><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17059/pic_article_birds13.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">I left the children and the adults celebrating in the park, one of the jewels of our city.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17060/pic_article_birds14.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>More photos in the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/deemopahan/media_set?set=a.10154130685433878.1073742695.587058877&amp;amp;type=3" target="_blank">FB album,</a> and the eBird list is <a href="http://ebird.org/ebird/view/checklist/S31790388" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Such urban nature walks show us the natural wealth that is still available to city-dwellers.</p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First 1000 garbage dumps in Bengaluru captured on crowdsourced map</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/first-1000-garbage-dumps-in-bengaluru-on-record-on-map-now</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/first-1000-garbage-dumps-in-bengaluru-on-record-on-map-now</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2016 06:44:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>News Desk</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/17006/small_dumpmap.png" /><br/><p>These 1000+ spots tell a thousand tales, if only someone has time to listen to each dump! Go explore the map, and see the stories for yourself.</p>]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/17006/small_dumpmap.png" /><p>This is surely a map no one wants to see. Nearly 1100 garbage dumps across different wards captured on a map, in the city of Bengaluru, by citizens - a crowdsourced attempt, point to how common and ubiquitous is the problem of garbage in public spaces.</p>
<p>Each garbage dump has a story behind it. Some of the photos from the map:</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16993/pic_article_horamavu_lake.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">What's happening near this lake?</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16991/pic_article_planned_landfill.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Thermocol is a type of waste Bengaluru cannot figure how to dispose. Dumped in a no-man's land, it slowly pollutes the atmosphere and water bodies.</p>
<p class="pic-caption"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16990/pic_article_milking_cow.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">A cow feeds on garbage full of paper and plastic. What milk are we drinking?</p>
<p class="pic-caption"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16992/pic_article_TUIfixLingarajapuram.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">When symptoms are fixed without fixing the root causes.</p>
<h3><strong>Champions who spearheaded the project:</strong></h3>
<div class="middle-column-special-box-right"><strong>One huge ward, 175 garbage dumps</strong><br />Bellandur ward, one of the biggest wards in Bengaluru, has an area of 26.4 sqkm. The volunteers in the ward captured more than 175 garbage dumps in their ward for this project. <br />The volunteers in the ward are also working towards <a href="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/blogs/forward-bellandur/blog_posts/trashonomics-101-ward-level-swm" target="_blank">responsible waste management</a>. Read <a href="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/blogs/forward-bellandur/blog_posts/trashonomics-101-ward-level-swm" target="_blank">their latest blog on the subject here</a>. Here are just a few Bangaloreans who have contributed to this project.</div>
<ul>
<li>Seema Sharma (mapping cordination- Bellandur)</li>
<li>Nitin Seshadri (mapping cordination - Koramangala)</li>
<li>MapBox team (mapping help - Indiranagar)</li>
<li>Gangadhar (mapping)</li>
<li>Kedar Thakar (mapping)</li>
<li>K Madhubala</li>
<li>Priyanka Bhatnagar (mapping)</li>
<li>Meera Nair (mapping)</li>
<li>Sumit Srivasthava (mapping)</li>
<li>Ravish Yavagal (mapping)</li>
<li>Nikita Vashisht (mapping)</li>
<li>Nisha Thompson (Mapping cordination)</li>
<li>Mapunity team (Tech support)</li>
<li>Nishanth C (mapping cordination, tech support)</li>
<li>And many, many more citizen volunteers who helped us put this map together, with their ideas, advices, suggestions and on-ground support, who preferred to remain anonymous.</li>
</ul>
<p>We can never thank all of them enough!<strong><br /></strong></p>
<p>According to Wikipedia, crowdsourcing is "a distributed problem-solving and production process that involves outsourcing tasks to a network of people, also known as the crowd".</p>
<p>Through this project we aimed at more citizen participation in solving the garbage issue, and what Bellandur team did is remarkable.</p>
<p>Like any other crowdsourced project, this project also will not be fully free of errors. But if the errors are pointed out, we will make the required corrections. <strong>We don't claim the data to be 100% accurate,</strong> but we will strive to make it better as and when we get data form people. You are welcome to send us updated photos and locations.</p>
<h3>Our comments:</h3>
<p>This is only the beginning, there's a long way to go. The BBMP has said there are 8000 blackspots in the city, and we would like to host all of them on our map! Do help us in this process. Right now,</p>
<p>1) The number of broken footpaths mapped here may not be covering all the broken footpaths in the area, as the focus was more on garbage dumps. <br /><strong>Update:</strong> We have removed the foootpath layer from this map, to represent only garbage dumps.</p>
<p>2) We have covered only a portion of the city. Most mapping activity happened on East, South, Mahadevpura and some parts of other zones. Other zones remain to be covered.</p>
<p>We need volunteers in West, South, Rajarajeshwari Nagar, Dasarahalli, Yelahanka and Bommanahalli Zones. which are yet to be mapped. Do install the app from <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.mapunity" target="_blank">Android playstore</a> or <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/in/app/mapunity-groups/id1094602497?mt=8" target="_blank">IOS appstore</a>, register yourself, join the group named 'Citizen Colab' and get going! <a href="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/why-are-we-mapping-garbage-dumps-in-bengaluru" target="_blank">Here are more details</a> about the project. <a href="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/why-are-we-mapping-garbage-dumps-in-bengaluru" target="_blank">To know more about how to get involved, click on this article.</a></p>
<p>If you have the data (photo and exact locations) and want to share it but don't want to use the app, <a href="mailto:citizencolab@oorvani.in" target="_blank">mail us</a>, we will figure out a way to take data from you.</p>
<p>If you are also the developer of an app or a belong to a project or a team that is into documenting garbage dumps, do join hands with us. It'll be a fun project - let's capture them all together and put them in one place for all to see! <a href="mailto:citizencolab@oorvani.in">Write to us</a>.</p>
<p>When we shared the idea of this project initially with BBMP officials in Solid Waste Management division, they gave a thumbs up to this. We will be sharing the existing data with BBMP soon, officially. We are as curious as you are, to see how this citizen-driven project can help solve the issues. Fingers crossed!</p>
<p>Click on each point in the map, read the description that appears in each of them, see the photo by clicking on the photo link. Explore the map. Do share your thoughts below this article. There may be some posts where photos are missing, due to technical issues.</p>
<p>If you see a garbage dump that is in the map, that has been recently cleared or fixed so that it is not a garbage dump anymore, you can login to the Mapunity app and comment with a new photo, under the same post. You can aslo do send us a photo and its location. Detailed base map from the data collection app is available <a href="http://citizen-co-lab.mapunitygroups.com/" target="_blank">here to see</a>.</p>
<p><iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/d/embed?mid=1ZDan4i_nwzJvLAAKy9w47JKwGyw" width="900" height="700"></iframe></p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bengaluru gears up for 'swachh-ta' on Gandhi Jayanti</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/bengaluru-gears-up-for-swachh-ta-on-gandhi-jayanti</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/bengaluru-gears-up-for-swachh-ta-on-gandhi-jayanti</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2016 06:22:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>News Desk</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16973/small_Swachh_Utsav.jpg" /><br/><p>If you want to pitch in to make your city cleaner this October 2nd, here's a list of missions around the city that you can join!</p>]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16973/small_Swachh_Utsav.jpg" /><p dir="ltr"><span><br /><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16973/Swachh_Utsav.jpg" alt="" /><br /></span></p>
<p class="pic-caption">&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr"><span>With just a day left for Gandhi Jayanti, various citizen led groups have planned to organise cleanliness programmes in various locations of Bengaluru on October 2nd.</span></p>
<p dir="ltr"><span>Here are the list of cleanliness programmes to be organised across the city as part of the Bengaluru Swachh Utsav 2016. The programme is organised by the Solid Waste Management Round Table in association with BBMP and KSPCB. The campaign which will be kicked off on the day of Gandhi Jayanti, will continue for the next one year, to create awareness about waste management among citizens.</span></p>
<p dir="ltr"><span>It includes, emphasising on door-to-door waste collection, green ambassador pledge, children&rsquo;s voices on branded litter, 2 Bin 1 Bag segregation, composting at home, mini talks and group selfie. The event will be held from 8 am to 6 pm. </span></p>
<p dir="ltr"><span>Interested citizens can visit their nearest event venue and be a part of the programme.</span></p>
<p dir="ltr"><span>Here is the list of locations where the </span><a href="https://www.facebook.com/SWMRTBangalore/?fref=ts"><span>Swachh Utsav </span></a><span>has been organised on October 2nd:</span></p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span>Byregowda Ranga Mandir, Jakkur Circle (Ward 5.7)</span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span>4th Main Road, Hoysala Nagar, Horamavu (Ward 25)</span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span>Chandrodaya Vidyalaya Institutions, Divanarapalya (Ward 35, 36, 45, 64,65,66, 76)</span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span>K R Puram Lake (Ward 52)</span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span>Milton Park (Ward 59)</span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span>Hagadur Inner Circle Road (Ward 84)</span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span>Government Boys&rsquo; School (Ward 85)</span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span>Sajjan Rao Circle (Ward 143)</span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span>Bhoomi College, Bellandur (Ward 150)</span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span>BBMP Office, Koramangala (Ward 151)</span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span>Bangalore One Office, HSR Layout (Ward 174)</span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span>Rose Garden, Puttenahalli (Ward 187)</span></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="ltr"><span>City-based NGO &ldquo;</span><a href="https://milaap.org/fundraisers/letsbethechange"><span>Let&rsquo;s be the Change</span></a><span>&rdquo; too is organising spot fixing programmes on the occasion of Gandhi Jayanti. The Biggest Cleanliness Drive will be organised at Kempegowda Bus Station on Sunday starting at 7 am. Over 350 volunteers are expected to participate in this cleanliness drive that intends to give a makeover to the Kempegowda Bus Station.</span></p>
<p><span id="docs-internal-guid-7909a937-7ed5-a58f-69b3-4e96a07fd18b"><span>Vasanthnagar Residents&rsquo; Welfare Association will host community cleanliness drives in the neighbourhood. The programme is supported by BBMP. The drive is &ldquo;to create an awareness among residents and owners of commercial establishments regarding waste management,&rdquo; says the Association&rsquo;s Facebook page.</span></span></p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Traffic cops, children worst hit by Bengaluru's air pollution</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/traffic-cops-children-worst-hit-by-bengaluru-air-pollution</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/traffic-cops-children-worst-hit-by-bengaluru-air-pollution</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 23:37:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Akshatha M</dc:creator>
      <dc:creator>Navya P K</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16971/small_air_pollution_1.jpg" /><br/><p>Several studies point to the disastrous effects of the city's deteriorating air quality on the health of its citizens and some particularly vulnerable groups.</p>]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16971/small_air_pollution_1.jpg" /><p dir="ltr"><span><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16971/pic_article_air_pollution_1.jpg" alt="" /><br /></span></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Air pollution on Outer Ring Road. Pic: Mayur Channagere</p>
<p class="pic-caption"><span style="color: #000000;">Air pollution in Bengaluru has become so severe, that it is forcing people with lung problems to even leave Bengaluru. Dr Padma Sundaram, pulmonologist at Manipal Hospital, says that some patients leave the city for months, to get better. She says that cases of asthma and respiratory infections are increasing, and that people with lung problems sometimes need ICU admissions when pollution levels peak, such as during winter smog and Diwali. &ldquo;People from highly polluted areas are coming for treatment more often,&rdquo; she says.</span></p>
<p><span>A lung test on 503 Bengaluru school children last year by the campaign CLAIM (Clean Air India Movement), found that only 11% of them had lungs in &lsquo;excellent&rsquo; condition; 36% students failed the test. </span><span>Studies by paediatric pulmonologist Dr H Paramesh have shown that pollution has a significant impact on lung health, especially among children and some occupational groups like traffic policemen.</span></p>
<p dir="ltr"><span>According to him, asthma prevalence among children in the city increased from 9% in 1979, to 25.6% in 2009. Also, allergic rhinitis increased from 20% to 27.5% in 10 years. Chronic coughing lasting more than two weeks, increased from 8% to 21% in 17 years.</span></p>
<p dir="ltr"><span>Dr Paramesh&rsquo;s studies show that the number of children affected by sinusitis, mouth breathing and sleep apnea has also increased; and so has the number of children affected by persistent, severe varieties of asthma. &ldquo;In the last 20 years, the number of children needing hospital admissions for asthma has increased from 4% to 11%,&rdquo; says Dr Paramesh.</span></p>
<p><span>His research also </span><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12019551" target="_blank"><span>found</span></a><span> that children faced a higher risk of asthma if they studied in schools located in areas that faced heavy traffic. The risk shot up further when the traffic factor was compounded by the low socioeconomic status of the children. Children from poorer households are affected more because they live in overcrowded, ill-ventilated houses, and also because they suffer from indoor pollution caused by the burning of firewood for cooking.</span></p>
<p>His studies also showed that asthma rates were highest among children living in urban areas, followed by those in semi-rural and rural areas (16.6%, 7.5% and 5.7% respectively). &ldquo;Within Bangalore, children from core areas suffer more. Sulphur dioxide and ozone are major irritants for the respiratory system. Ozone is formed more around traffic signals, when bright sunlight interacts with vehicular pollutants. This may be contributing to the rise in asthma cases among children during summer,&rdquo; says Dr Paramesh.</p>
<p>His study among policemen showed that asthma rate was higher among traffic policemen than non-traffic policemen (26% vs 15%), as also was the case with cough, rhinitis and breathlessness.</p>
<h3><strong>It&rsquo;s not just your lung that is affected!</strong></h3>
<p><span>While air pollution is known to cause lung problems, there is much less awareness about its conclusive links with premature deaths, heart diseases, stroke etc. Scientific evidence has been highest against PM</span><span>2.5</span><span> - fine particles with diameter less than 2.5 micrometer, made up of many toxic metals and acids.</span></p>
<p dir="ltr"><span>Data from AQI (Air Quality Index) monitoring stations in the city shows that PM</span><span>2.5</span><span> is above limits on most days. In fact, AQI usually exceeds standards because of high levels of PM</span><span>2.5</span><span> and PM</span><span>10 </span><span>(relatively bigger particles with diameter less than 10 micrometer). AQI stations in the city show no data on many days, but on days that data is available, PM</span><span>2.5</span><span> often quite easily crosses levels of 100 &micro;g/m</span><span>3</span><span>.</span></p>
<p><span>For example, on July 6th, the BTM AQI station recorded maximum levels of 420 &micro;g/m</span><span>3</span><span>. This station had earlier recorded levels of even 500 &micro;g/m</span><span>3</span><span>, the maximum value that can possibly be recorded under AQI. Around July 6th, two other AQI stations that monitor PM</span><span>2.5</span><span>, at Peenya and BWSSB Kadubeesanahalli, showed maximum levels of 115 and 153 &micro;g/m</span><span>3</span><span> respectively.</span></p>
<p><span>The average levels of PM</span><span>2.5</span><span> in a day should be below 30 &micro;g/m</span><span>3 </span><span>for it to be in &ldquo;good&rdquo; category as per AQI. But data from the Karnataka State Pollution Control Board (KSPCB) for 2015-16 shows that annual averages of PM</span><span>2.5 </span><a href="http://www.kspcb.gov.in/AQI-DATA-Bangalore-CITY-2015-16.pdf" target="_blank"><span>were in the range of 50-70 &micro;g/m</span><span>3</span></a><span>in most parts of the city. And even though, technically, limits are set for PM</span><span>2.5</span><span>, according to the WHO there is no level at which PM</span><span>2.5</span><span> does not cause any harm.</span></p>
<p><span>According to WHO, &nbsp;PM</span><span>2.5</span><span> is the fifth biggest risk factor for death in India. WHO&rsquo;s Global Burden of Disease (GBD) study revealed that 6.27 lakh people died in India due to ambient (outdoor) PM</span><span>2.5</span><span>, in 2010 (6% of the total deaths). The deaths were mostly from heart diseases, especially Ischemic Heart Disease (IHD) wherein plaque deposits in blood vessels reduce blood flow to the heart. A quarter of the deaths were from respiratory diseases. PM</span><span>2.5</span><span> also majorly contributed to Acute Lower Respiratory Infections (ALRI) among children under five years, which can be fatal.</span></p>
<p dir="ltr">Dr Narendra Rangappa, Orthopaedic and Senior Consultant at Fortis Hospital who also practices community medicine, says that the number of youngsters prone to heart attack has increased over the years. &ldquo;A lot of young people in the early decades of their life undergo bypass surgery, and certainly air pollution is one of the major reasons for it. &nbsp;Nitrogen oxide (from vehicles) and sulfur dioxide (from industries and fuel combustion) in the air causes cardiovascular diseases. Gas boilers at home emit carbon monoxide. Burning of garbage and waste too emits harmful substances,&rdquo; he says.</p>
<h3><strong>Differentiating between particulate matter</strong></h3>
<p dir="ltr"><span>Though both PM</span><span>10</span><span> and PM</span><span>2.5</span><span> are both dangerous, PM</span><span>2.5</span><span> is more harmful because of its small size which allows it to penetrate deeper into the lungs and enter the bloodstream. PM</span><span>2.5</span><span> is linked more with heart diseases, and PM</span><span>10</span><span> more with respiratory diseases like bronchitis, asthma, lung cancer etc.</span></p>
<p>Studies in the US and Europe in the 90s showed that PM by itself could cause cardiovascular diseases, without any additional factors, either suddenly (like a heart attack) or over time.</p>
<p><span>A major long-term study - the </span><a href="http://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJM199312093292401#t=abstract" target="_blank"><span>Harvard Six Cities Study</span></a><span> that tracked 8000 adults in six US cities over 14-16 years, It found that the most polluted city&rsquo;s death rate was 26% higher than that of the least polluted city. The highest number of deaths were from cardiovascular diseases, and then from lung cancer and cardiopulmonary diseases. This study led to the regulation of PM</span><span>2.5</span><span> in US. Another </span><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11879110" target="_blank"><span>study</span></a><span> by the American Cancer Society among 50 lakh adults found that hike in PM</span><span>2.5 </span><span>levels was linked with deaths from lung cancer, cardiopulmonary diseases and deaths from all causes.</span></p>
<p><span>The main source of PM</span><span>2.5 </span><span>in Bangalore is vehicle pollution, while that of PM</span><span>10</span><span> is road dust. Like PM</span><span>2.5</span><span>, PM</span><span>10</span><span> also exceeds standards very often under AQI monitoring. Air quality monitoring in 2015-16 </span><a href="http://kspcb.kar.nic.in/AQI-DATA-Bangalore-CITY-2015-16.pdf" target="_blank"><span>shows</span></a><span> that PM</span><span>10</span><span> (RSPM) levels were 2-3 times the standard in most locations.</span></p>
<p><span>An </span><a href="http://www.iimahd.ernet.in/~dhiman/pollution_mortality.pdf" target="_blank"><span>IIM study</span></a><span> in the city in 2008-09 showed that, with every increase of 10 &micro;g/m</span><span>3</span><span> in daily average levels of PM</span><span>10</span><span>, the daily death rate increased by 0.22%. The city&rsquo;s high population and high levels of PM</span><span>10</span><span> would mean that this will translate to a high number of premature deaths. Other Indian metros show similar patterns.</span></p>
<p><span>Notably, current Indian standards for pollutants have much higher thresholds than that of developed countries. For example, the </span><a href="http://cpcb.nic.in/National_Ambient_Air_Quality_Standards.php" target="_blank"><span>Indian standard</span></a><span> for annual average PM</span><span>2.5</span><span> is 40 &micro;g/m</span><span>3</span><span>, compared to the WHO guideline of 10 &micro;g/m</span><span>3</span><span>, and US national standard of 15 &micro;g/m</span><span>3</span><span>. India faces many challenges in reducing pollution, and hence cannot lower its standards immediately.</span></p>
<h3><strong>Pollution and cancer?</strong></h3>
<p dir="ltr"><span>In 2013, &nbsp;the IARC (International Agency for Research on Cancer) - WHO&rsquo;s cancer agency - confirmed the close link of PM with higher rates of lung and urinary tract/bladder cancers.</span></p>
<p dir="ltr"><span>A Hyderabad </span><a href="http://icmr.nic.in/ijmr/2009/november/1105.pdf" target="_blank"><span>study</span></a><span> in 2002-06 found that vehicular emissions caused mutations in the cellular chromosomes of traffic policemen, which could lead to cancer. The study had compared traffic policemen with office workers, and found that the policemen had twice the level of chromosomal mutations as office workers. </span><a href="http://icmr.nic.in/ijmr/2009/november/1101.pdf" target="_blank"><span>Commenting</span></a><span> on this study, ICMR (Indian Council of Medical Research) said that recent trends in childhood cancer could mean that children were more at risk from pollution.</span></p>
<p dir="ltr"><span>A </span><a href="http://www.ncrpindia.org/ALL_NCRP_REPORTS/TREND_REPORT_1982_2010/ALL_CONTENT/Main.htm" target="_blank"><span>trend report</span></a><span> by NCPR (National Cancer Registry Programme) shows that in 2008-09 lung cancer became the most common type of cancer among Bengaluru men, which was only the third most common type in 1982-83. The report shows a steep upward trend in lung cancer cases among both Bengaluru men and women since the late 90s. Cases of other types of cancer have also increased. </span></p>
<p dir="ltr"><span>Dr Niti Raizada, Medical Oncologist and Hem-Oncologist Senior Consultant at Fortis and Vikram Group of Hospitals, says air pollution can cause a range of cancers, not just lung cancer. &ldquo;Pollutants from petro-chemical industry can cause liver cancer, it can also lead to brain tumours and blood cancer. Benzene emitted from crude oil and burning of certain plastics can result in Leukaemia. Kidney, skin and bladder cancer can be a result of arsenic content in the air. </span><span>Pollution emitted from mining may lead to lung and pleural cancer,&rdquo; s</span><span>he observes.</span></p>
<h3 dir="ltr"><strong>Indoor pollution</strong></h3>
<p>In the city, many households, especially poorer ones, use kerosene as cooking fuel, which increases their exposure to indoor pollution. A 2004-05 study of 600 Koramangala households found that women and children in households that used kerosene were at higher risk of respiratory illnesses. About one-third of these households were using only kerosene while the rest used LPG. Women who used kerosene had more frequent cough and chest illness, and children from these households suffered more from bronchitis and phlegm.</p>
<p><span>According to the GBD report, Household Air Pollution (HAP) is even more harmful than outdoor pollution. The report ranks HAP the second highest risk factor for death in India, causing one million deaths annually. HAP also contributes majorly to ambient PM</span><span>2.5</span><span>.</span></p>
<h3><strong>Pollutants galore</strong></h3>
<p><span>Other than PM, Carbon Monoxide (CO) and ozone are observed in high levels in Bengaluru, according to the NGO Greenpeace&rsquo;s </span><a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/india/Global/india/2015/docs/India-NAQI-PRESS.pdf" target="_blank"><span>analysis</span></a><span> of the city&rsquo;s AQI readings of April-November 2015. A 2007 </span><a href="http://www.cpcb.nic.in/Bangalore.pdf" target="_blank"><span>study</span></a><span> by TERI in Bengaluru, commissioned by the Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB), had also found high CO and ozone levels.</span></p>
<h3><strong>What&rsquo;s the solution?</strong></h3>
<p><span>India&rsquo;s air quality is so bad that even aggressive measures will not help it immediately, </span><a href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/pdf/10.1021/acs.est.5b01236" target="_blank"><span>according to</span></a><span> Aaron Cohen who was part of the GBD study, and others. They say that even bringing down PM</span><span>2.5</span><span> levels by 20-30% over the next 15 years would only keep the current death rates constant, and will not reduce it. But they say that initial regulations can be introduced at a relatively low cost, which will help in the long term.</span></p>
<p><span><span>Dr Bobby Joseph, HOD at the Department of Community Medicine at St John&rsquo;s Medical College, says that high pollution levels have not led to changed behavioural responses among Bengalureans. &ldquo;This could be because the impacts of pollution are not directly visible,&rdquo; he says. Even individual decisions like not buying diesel cars or just switching off vehicles at traffic junctions could go a long way in reducing pollution.</span></span></p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bengaluru activists plan satyagraha campaign against genetically modified mustard</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/a-new-satyagraha-this-october-2-will-you-join</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/a-new-satyagraha-this-october-2-will-you-join</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 05:33:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>News Desk</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16962/small_GM_Mustard.jpg" /><br/><p>A coalition against GM food crops has planned a citizens' awareness and call-to-action campaign to be launched on October 2.</p>]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16962/small_GM_Mustard.jpg" /><p dir="ltr"><span data-mce-mark="1"><br /><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16962/GM_Mustard.jpg" alt="" /><br /></span></p>
<p class="pic-caption">&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr"><span>GM-Free Karnataka and the Karnataka Alliance for Safe Food have announced a 'Sasive Satyagraha' event in Bangalore on October 2, 2016, to be held at the Gandhi Statue at &nbsp;Anand Rao Circle, Bangalore from 10:30 a.m. to 4 p.m. This is primarily a citizens' awareness and call-to-action campaign to protest against the approval of the commercial release of genetically modified varieties of mustard (GM Mustard) in the country. </span></p>
<p>The fight against genetically modified food has just been revived with renewed vigour around the country, with activists and experts raising strong opposition to the introduction of GM Mustard. The commercial cultivation of GM mustard in India could soon be approved by the Indian government, especially after the publication of a report, &ldquo;Assessment of Food and Environmental Safety for Environmental Release of Genetically Engineered Mustard (Brassica juncea) hybrid DMH-11.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A note published on the website of the Ministry for environment Forests and climate change confirms that the Centre for Genetic Manipulation of Crop Plants (CGMCP) in New Delhi has applied for the approval of the environmental release of three genetically modified varieties of mustard to the Genetic Engineering Appraisal Committee (GEAC).</p>
<p><span data-mce-mark="1">A </span><a href="https://www.change.org/p/anilmdave-indian-govt-say-no-to-gm-mustard?recruiter=12813161&amp;utm_source=share_petition&amp;utm_medium=facebook&amp;utm_campaign=share_facebook_responsive&amp;utm_term=mob-xs-share_petition-custom_msg&amp;fb_ref=Default"><span data-mce-mark="1">petition</span></a><span data-mce-mark="1"> on change.org which has already garnered signatures from 18,386 supporters (and counting) raises the most frequent concerns of those against the approval of the three GMOs. For one thing, it is felt that once GM Mustard is approved, it will only make the way smoother for the introduction of many more GM food crops &ndash; maize, rice, jowar, wheat, brinjal etc.</span></p>
<p>The health and environmental impacts of genetic modification have long been suspect among a large section of society and the petitioners in this case too believe that the negative effects of GM mustard have been suppressed. To lend strength to their argument, they point to the fact that even the major mustard growing states of &nbsp;Rajasthan, Madhya Pradesh, Punjab and Haryana have said no to experimental trials of the GM crop.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, organisers of the Bengaluru rally, too, have come out vociferously opposing GM mustard. They have released a detailed 8-point rationalisation of why all citizens should staunchly protest its commercial release. The objections raised by them are as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span data-mce-mark="1">Transgenic technology is unsafe and irreversible; Environmental release of GMOs increases risk in agriculture, and takes away choices both for farmers and consumers. It is noteworthy that 17 of the 20 most developed countries do not cultivate GM crops.</span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span data-mce-mark="1">The testing of GM mustard is unscientific, inadequate &amp; unreliable; claims of yield increase are also unverified</span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span data-mce-mark="1">Containment of GM mustard is impossible and contamination, both biological and physical, inevitable; this reduces farmer choices and consumers&rsquo; right to know what is in their food</span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span data-mce-mark="1">The current set of 3 mustard GMOs are all herbicide-tolerant crops but the application does not declare them so. GM Mustard could well imply backdoor entry for Herbicide Tolerant (HT) crops, which result in more herbicide use, higher toxic residues in food, prevent mixed cropping, damage crops in neighbouring farms, and destroy income that can be earned by manual weeding by women agricultural workers. </span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span data-mce-mark="1">State Governments, including leading mustard-growing states, more than 50 large and active farmer unions of the country and scores of scientists have written to the government against permitting any release of GM mustard. Ordinary citizens too have been writing in thousands to the government resisting the approval of GM mustard. </span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span data-mce-mark="1">State Governments, including leading mustard-growing states, more than 50 large and active farmer unions of the country and scores of scientists have written to the government against permitting any release of GM mustard. Ordinary citizens too have been writing in thousands to the government resisting the approval of GM mustard. </span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span data-mce-mark="1">GM mustard will impact honey bees and the sunrise honey industry adversely. Bee-keeping with mustard increases yields of mustard by about 20-25%, even as it supports honey production and additional income for the beekeeper. GM mustard has potential adverse impacts on honey bees.</span></p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr"><span data-mce-mark="1">The applicants of GM mustard claim that approval for their transgenics will lead to increase in India&rsquo;s yields and production of rapeseed mustard and will thereby bring down the country&rsquo;s edible oil import bill. However, official records show that release of (non-GM) hybrids into the market has not resulted in either production increase or in import bill declines.</span></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The Coalition for a GM-free India also points out that the biotech regulator GEAC has not cleaned itself of conflict of interest, with one member from the GM applicant team also being a GEAC member. Test protocols were prescribed by the crop developers themselves.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, data is shrouded in secrecy. Test results have not been shared in public despite orders from the Supreme Court and the Central Information Commission that require the regulators to put out data for public scrutiny.</p>
<p>It is in view of all the above that the Karnataka coalition has urged citizens to join in the Sasive Satyagraha event scheduled. It will be a one-day protest led by the Karnataka State Farmers Association - KRRS (Karnataka Rajya Raitha Sangha) marked by day-long fasting by the gathering.</p>
<p>There will be a poster exhibition on the hazards of GMOs in general and in particular GM Mustard, along with a display of different varieties of Mustard grown in the state of Karnataka.</p>
<p>At the end of the event, a delegation will go the Chief Minister&rsquo;s office with a memorandum to be handed over to the CM urging him to act on behalf of the citizens (farmers and consumers) of Karnataka, asking the Prime Minister to ban GM Mustard and stop its commercial release.</p>
<p>A 'missed call' campaign is also underway, where citizens can register their protest against the release of the crop&nbsp;<span>by dialling the number 044-33124242.</span></p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What you eat and how that can help farmers</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/how-can-we-support-farmers</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/how-can-we-support-farmers</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 07:48:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Priya Ramasubban</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16906/small_Vegetable_Cart_in_Guntur.jpg" /><br/><p>What we eat every day is what affects farmers. Think about how we can make long term choices to support them every day of the year!</p>]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16906/small_Vegetable_Cart_in_Guntur.jpg" /><p>It was an enlightening thing to go through the vitriol and acrimony of the messages during the bandh, and in the last few days. &nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">As someone whose family has been in farming, I urge all of you to think about supporting farmers every day of the year.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The easiest and most effective way to do so is by eating local produce -- from millets to leafy greens to gourds. Traditionally, native grains and vegetables have been varieties that have used very little water to grow, and are extremely healthy for us. Our state's cuisine include staples like ragi and jowar that we urban dwellers have either forgotten or rarely eat. It's a rich source of nutrition and also <a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/cover-story/a-millets-revival-could-solve-indias-malnutrition-problem-benefit-farmers-31717">uses VERY little water</a> compared to the white rice (or even brown rice) most of you probably eat.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><a href="http://www.ripublication.com/ijafst_spl/ijafstv4n5spl_16.pdf">Eating soppu</a> like honagone, chakramuni, agasi, basale&hellip; or vegetables like heerekai, hagalkai, thondekai, etc, on a regular basis will keep us in good health, and also have a huge impact on water use in farms.</p>
<p style="margin-left: 30px;" dir="ltr">"Moringa oleifera or drumstick leaves widely grown in India... It is a rich source of many micronutrients &ndash; beta carotene, folic acid, calcium, iron and vitamin C and it also provides good quality protein. "</p>
<p style="margin-left: 30px;" dir="ltr">Source: <a href="http://www.fao.org/3/a-i3685e.pdf">Food and Agriculture Organisation Report</a></p>
<p dir="ltr">Instead, we now buy <a href="http://food.ndtv.com/food-drinks/the-12-most-pesticide-contaminated-fruits-and-vegetables-of-2015-752555">colourful capsicum, potatoes, cauliflower, french beans, musk melon</a>, etc...all of which use heavy pesticides and fertilisers...which sucks moisture out of our soils...which then need huge amount of water to keep hydrated.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Our agricultural policies on the central level need to be opposed as they make farmers dependent on chemical fertiliser and pesticides. If we reverse the subsidies to these huge chemical companies, our efforts towards water neutrality will go a long way.</p>
<p dir="ltr">There are local, state level and national level issues we can all engage in.</p>
<p dir="ltr">At the local level, please buy from organic farmers cooperatives (like Jaivik Krishik Society). This helps farmers DIRECTLY. <a href="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/more-shops-better-prices-informed-consumers-organic-food-getting-mainstream">Jaivik has a store</a> at Lalbagh and have set up stall at Cubbon Park during weekends. If enough of you are interested, ask them to open a branch in your neighbourhood. There are also many privately owned organic <a href="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/more-shops-better-prices-informed-consumers-organic-food-getting-mainstream">stores</a> in many areas. You also have the option of buying organic produce from new startups that <a href="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/organic-farming-bangalore-movement">directly connect to farmers</a>.</p>
<p dir="ltr">At the state level, ask agricultural universities to not emphasise on chemical intensive teaching and instead encourage teaching traditional farming practises which use less water and grow what is naturally suited using available biomass as fodder and nutrition for the soil.</p>
<p dir="ltr">On a national level please engage to fight genetically modified crops and the chemical fertiliser industry.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Whatever your position on the bandh was...it 'seemed' like everyone was FOR farmers. What we eat everyday is what affects farmers. If everyone supports farmers think about how we can make long term choices to support them every day of the year and not just one day during the bandh.</p>
<p dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why are we mapping garbage dumps in Bengaluru?</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/why-are-we-mapping-garbage-dumps-in-bengaluru</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/why-are-we-mapping-garbage-dumps-in-bengaluru</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 11:38:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Shree D N</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16892/small_ejipura1.jpg" /><br/><p>A garbage dump symbolises the problem in the waste collection system. A city can try to solve the garbage problem, with the help of authentic data marked on map.</p>]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16892/small_ejipura1.jpg" /><p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16891/pic_article_screenshot.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>We launched the crowdsourced <a href="http://citizen-co-lab.mapunitygroups.com/" target="_blank">Blackspot Mapping Project</a> (garbage dump mapping project) in the last week of August, 2016. Two weeks into the project, we are already nearing 200 spots. As we reached out to people for help, we also faced many questions: Why are you doing this? What&rsquo;s the intent? What will this data be used for? So many apps to map garbage and other issues - why should we contribute data to this project? In this article, we try to explain it all in detail.</p>
<h3>Why are you doing this? What&rsquo;s the intent?</h3>
<p>Our cities suffer from multiple problems. Especially a mega-city of 10 million people like Bengaluru has so many issues waiting to be solved, and new ones cropping up. Data about the problems can help solve them, but the government doesn't have the mechanism and bandwidth to collect enough ground level data about issues. So how do we collect useful data? How do we get the governments to address them?</p>
<p>A <em>Citizen Matters</em> and <a href="http://datameet.org/" target="_blank">Datameet</a> initiative, <a href="http://opencity.in" target="_blank">Opencity.in</a> is one such attempt, to put more and more data in the public domain. As a pilot project, <em>Citizen Matters</em> has taken up the most pertinent problem Bengaluru is facing - garbage problem.</p>
<p>The data is crowdsourced from interested readers of <em>Citizen Matters</em> and people who perceive the issue of solid waste management in this city to be a serious one that needs effort and attention. It's basically a people's project. We are only putting it all together in one place and presenting it, for all to see. <strong>Our intent is to help the city solve the issue, with the help of authentic data marked on map</strong>.</p>
<h3>What will this data be used for?</h3>
<p>Bengaluru often sees open <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/d/viewer?mid=1fZ0VyjkdZr4x-7NGDA_1A9-p4J4&amp;usp=sharing" target="_blank">burning of garbage</a> in all parts of the city, especially in winter, causing enormous pollution. Garbage dumps, or blackspots are also the brutal deciders of the efficiency of garbage collection system. This project aims to map the blackspots in the city and put it in the public domain, so that whoever wants to address the issue can take action.</p>
<p>What can be done, and by whom? Citizens can work towards fixing the blackspots through 'spotfixes'. The city administration, Bruhat Bengaluru Mahanagara Palike (BBMP) can look at the micro-management plan for the areas where there are garbage blackspots, improve waste collection systems and take other required steps. The higher-level administration can look at the data, figure out patterns and see if there's anything to be done to solve the issue.</p>
<p>There are multiple possibilities here. The indication of the efficiency and effectiveness of the measures taken is again the presence or elimination of the garbage dump. The data in the form of photos and observations will help evaluate the situation over time, as this project has the scope for adding timelines in the form of more photos and comments over time.</p>
<h3>What's the difference between other apps and this?</h3>
<p>True, there are many other apps meant for blackspot mapping. The main difference between them and this project is this: the data collected in other apps is not in the public domain. Once you enter the data in an app, it is fed into the system, generally you will be given a complaint number and phone numbers, if it is an app that promises you to fix the problem. The cases are treated as individual, and temporary, and there is no attempt to look at it as a pertinent problem, for which long term solutions and systemic fixes are required.</p>
<p>As a result, nobody knows how many garbage blackspots (dumps) the city has. And no one knows how serious the issue is, the reasons and what needs to be done about it. Hence this project, to map it all and put it online, to SEE the problem on a map.</p>
<p>This is an open data project. The primary app we use for dta collection is going to be MapunityGroups. This app requires your email id for registration, does not ask for phone numbers. You can post even anonymously.</p>
<p>The data collected from the project will be published on <a href="http://opencity.in" target="_blank">Opencity.in</a> website, and on <a href="http://mapunity.org" target="_blank">Mapunity.org</a>. The data will be governed by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_data" target="_blank">Open Data policies</a>.</p>
<h3>Okay, I feel this will be useful, and I want to contribute.</h3>
<p>You can be a part of this fun mapping-cum-public problem recording project. To contribute, all you have to do is to share with us geotagged photos of blackspots, with address, date and time, ward.</p>
<p>To make the data collection and presentation easy, we are using a form prepared in MapunityGroups app. If you want to go for this app, here is what you need to do:</p>
<p><strong>1. Download the app.</strong></p>
<p>Link to Mapunity Groups IOS app: <strong><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/in/app/mapunity-groups/id1094602497?mt=8" target="_blank">https://itunes.apple.com/in/app/mapunity-groups/id1094602497?mt=8</a></strong></p>
<p>Link to Mapunity Groups Android app: <strong><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.mapunity" target="_blank">https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.mapunity</a></strong></p>
<p><strong>2. Sign up and join the group Citizen Co-Lab.</strong></p>
<p>Here are the detailed instructions to mappers:</p>
<p><strong>Android instructions:</strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1elyFX1e6g1K_oYz1KxMszmPb3Ox-fXkPAYx-bH9Oni4/pub" target="_blank">https://docs.google.com/document/d/1elyFX1e6g1K_oYz1KxMszmPb3Ox-fXkPAYx-bH9Oni4/pub</a></strong></p>
<p><strong>iPhone instructions:</strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1SF07b7sW60gTMxqxwfUiNQuTPEsKvMvgcdJLrYeU1BY/pub" target="_blank">https://docs.google.com/document/d/1SF07b7sW60gTMxqxwfUiNQuTPEsKvMvgcdJLrYeU1BY/pub</a></strong></p>
<p><strong>3. Shoot blackspots or problem spots, on your camera and put them on the map.</strong></p>
<p>The map will be visible here on web: <strong><a href="http://citizen-co-lab.mapunitygroups.com/" target="_blank">http://citizen-co-lab.mapunitygroups.com</a></strong></p>
<p><strong>Note:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>You can check the ward boundaries here: <strong><a href="http://bcity.in/wards" target="_blank">http://bcity.in/wards</a></strong></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The Android and IOS versions of the MapunityGroups app may have some minor usability issues. Please report any bugs you find, along with screenshots, <strong><a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSedQxLVIE9RdfclGG0o5NjY-HjAMpNw8gms8xIRe32H2hBNHg/viewform" target="_blank">using this form.</a></strong></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>What are blackspots?</h3>
<p>For the sake our project, we are taking BBMP's official definition of a blackspot. Blackspots are areas where garbage is dumped daily, either by citizens or by garbage contract workers, or by BBMP workers. A garbage spot qualifies as a blackspot even if it is cleared daily, because it is a symptom of inefficiency of garbage collection system and needs solutions.</p>
<p><strong>What are Problem spots?</strong></p>
<p>Since the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.mapunity&amp;hl=en" target="_blank">Mapunity Groups</a> app we are using has the capability to map any issue in the city, we have expanded the scope. When you try to post the data, you will see two layers. They are,</p>
<ul>
<li>Problem Spots in Bengaluru</li>
<li class="_mce_tagged_br">Blackspots in Bengaluru</li>
</ul>
<p>Problem spots, as we have defined for the sake of this project, are areas on footpaths that are:</p>
<ul>
<li>filled with construction rubble, mud or debris,</li>
<li class="_mce_tagged_br">having unwalkable footpaths, broken footpath slabs etc.</li>
</ul>
<p>Black Spots and Problem Spots are in different layers, or two different templates, so you can choose to map both as you go on.</p>
<h3>Can we map anonymously?</h3>
<p>Yes, currently we are allowing it in the app. As long as the data you provide is authentic, it doesn't matter who provides them. We have enabled moderation so that admins can check each spot before taking it live. Having said this, we might remove the option of anonymity if there is too much junk data coming in anonymously.</p>
<p>The downside of mapping anonymously is that you will not be able to update the blackspot you post, if a spot is eliminated by BBMP or citizens.</p>
<h3>Is the app recommended by you the only way to share data?</h3>
<p>No. You can share photos, location, date and time of capture, description of the spot, address etc in an excel. You can collect this data manually or using any app you want. Even geotagged photos and Tweets are acceptable. Tweet to <strong><a href="https://twitter.com/citizenmatters" target="_blank">us</a></strong> the geotagged photos, with a line of description, using the hashtag #BBMPBlackspot. Or email the geotagged photos to <a href="mailto:citizencolab@oorvani.in" target="_blank">citizencolab@oorvani.in</a></p>
<p>If you have data, and want to share it, but don&rsquo;t want to use the app recommended by us, you can reach out to us on <a href="mailto:citizencolab@oorvani.in" target="_blank">citizencolab@oorvani.in</a>.</p>
<p>We will be planning a Data Party soon, where people can gather in different parts of the city, and go mapping. More on that soon, but meanwhile you can start the process on your own. The app currently has 30 mappers, and about 200 spots mapped.</p>
<p>We hope to make this project an example of utilisation of public data in problem-solving. Do join us in this journey!</p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>There is only one person who can ensure a Swachh Bharat: You!</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/there-is-only-one-person-who-can-ensure-a-swachh-bharat-you</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/there-is-only-one-person-who-can-ensure-a-swachh-bharat-you</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2016 07:28:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Sudha Narasimhachar</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16877/small_swacchbharat.jpg" /><br/><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-19bec65b-0896-fabd-d14e-9f044cf312e0"><span>The Prime Minister&rsquo;s vision of a clean India will remain a pipe dream unless the common man takes it upon himself.</span></span></p>]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16877/small_swacchbharat.jpg" /><p dir="ltr"><span data-mce-mark="1">&lsquo;Swacch Bharat!&rsquo; We have seen a lot of hype about this programme in media but what is the reality? Of course, many things are happening in little pockets around the country, about which we read or hear. It does give us some hope that some day, maybe after half a century, we may see some difference at least in certain localities. However, as an individual, my experience has been a bit disappointing.</span></p>
<p>Firstly, the once beautiful garden city of Bengaluru is turning into a city of concrete, garbage, polluted water bodies and chaos at a very fast pace! &nbsp;Cleaning up the existing dirt is one thing. &nbsp;But unless our people develop a mindset against creating more filth, Prime Minister Narendra Modi&rsquo;s dream is going to be really tough to realise.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16877/pic_article_swacchbharat.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Pic: Shree D N</p>
<p><span data-mce-mark="1">In Singapore, </span><a href="http://www.mot.gov.sg/News-Centre/News/2009/Question-for-Written-Answer(11)/"><span data-mce-mark="1">people cannot eat or drink anything in public transport vehicles and the fine for breaking this rule could go up to as much as 500 Singapore Dollars</span></a><span data-mce-mark="1">! Can we ever implement a law so strictly? &nbsp;Modi and his team have been harping on stopping the menace of open defecation in rural areas. But according to me, urban spaces are the dirtiest, and not just in and around the slums. &nbsp;</span></p>
<p>How much can Government agencies alone achieve? Educated people and students do not think twice before urinating in any public place. People litter the roads and the space outside shopping complexes without hesitation. &nbsp;If we try to advise them, we are snubbed, &lsquo;mind your business&rsquo;. Besides, we cannot police every citizen against littering, spitting, urinating and defecating in public. Unless people themselves are aware and cooperative, this is going to be an utter failure.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The Railways are really working hard to fulfil this dream. The stations generally are clean. I was very surprised to find very clean toilets, with water supply, buckets and mugs at Erode Junction, where I had to wait for a train recently. &nbsp;But so much more needs to be done. The second class compartments were very unclean. &nbsp;There was no water in one of the toilets and my complaint went unheard. There are no mugs. There are no garbage-bins. &nbsp;</p>
<p>As it is, people rarely use bins to throw trash! Most find it easier to throw the plastic packets, cups, plates and leftover food items on the railway track, to save those few steps to the nearest bin! So, imagine the scene when there is no bin around!</p>
<p><span data-mce-mark="1">The entire railway track is littered and it is sad to see employees of the railways clearing the trash physically, who anyway have to bear the misery of walking on these tracks laden with human faeces and urine from the train toilets.</span><span data-mce-mark="1">When will our people realise that a bit of discipline on their part could greatly reduce the ordeal of these individuals?</span></p>
<p>Modi&rsquo;s grandiose dream also encompasses cleaning of the holy river Ganga. May this happen! But in a country, where people are capable of dirtying even an ocean, God save the rivers and lakes! I visited Rameshwaram temple recently and had the shock of my life. The temple is very well-maintained, clean and orderly. But there is a practice or ritual that mandates devotees to bathe in the ocean behind the temple, then bathe in the water of the twenty two wells situated inside the temple and then go into the temple in dry clothes for worshipping Lord Ramanatha. &nbsp;So, we went to the shore of the ocean first and were shocked to see the crowd and filth there. &nbsp;</p>
<p><span data-mce-mark="1">First of all,&nbsp;</span><span data-mce-mark="1">the water is stagnant, without waves and seems like the backwaters.</span><span data-mce-mark="1"> We stepped in, thinking that we would go farther into the water to avoid the dirty shoreline, as it was shallow, but even after we walked nearly two furlongs into the ocean, we were stepping on clothes - used clothes! It then emerged that there is a belief that one should forsake the old clothes that he or she is wearing before going inside the temple. So, people just throw the clothes into the water or dump them all along the shore and even in the changing rooms inside the temple! &nbsp;</span></p>
<p>I have nothing to say against individual religious beliefs. But, there could be a more sustainable way to put them into practice. Can the authorities not have an arrangement to collect such clothes and have them disposed of by better methods? &nbsp;How can they be blind to millions of people dumping their clothes into the still waters of the ocean? &nbsp;How dirty it is to walk on those dirty, mossy clothes? &nbsp;How holy will you be after such a dirty bath? &nbsp;Isn&rsquo;t it also unhygienic? &nbsp;</p>
<p>I feel really sad that all our water bodies are polluted in some way or the other - religious beliefs, industrial waste, urban sewage and the general bad habits of the public have all combined to bring them to this state. Swanky high-rise complexes are constructed right on the banks of water bodies and the sewage waste is very conveniently directed to the water bodies. Unless we stop all this nonsense, we have no hope of seeing the light of a cleaner, better tomorrow. &nbsp;</p>
<p><span id="docs-internal-guid-19bec65b-0899-8ff4-6834-cb5c3b73d980"><span>Each of us should make it a habit to respect public spaces, water bodies, forests and mountains. &nbsp;Only then, can we clean up our country. &nbsp;Modi alone or his slogans, his laws and his team can achieve little without the cooperation of the common man!</span></span></p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> Painted Grasshopper: a marvel of the insect world!</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/painted-grasshoppers-images-description</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/painted-grasshoppers-images-description</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2016 03:30:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Deepa Mohan</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16875/small_painted_grasshopper3.jpg" /><br/><p>Seen these colourful locusts anywhere ever? They are extraordinarily sensitive to their surroundings, and can jump about a metre without wings!</p>]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16875/small_painted_grasshopper3.jpg" /><p>Sometimes dry, barren-seeming patches of land have so much of interest in them. Recently, my friend Manivannan S spotted, in a small empty lot, this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poekilocerus_pictus"> Painted Grasshopper. </a></p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16873/pic_article_painted_grasshopper1.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>The wiki entry on this gorgeous-looking creature says that the grasshopper feeds on the poisonous plant <em>Calotropis gigantea.</em></p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16874/pic_article_painted_grasshopper2.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>Certainly, these grasshoppers had stripped all the <em>Calatropis</em> (milkweed) plants nearby. Striking in appearance... The mature grasshopper has canary yellow and turquoise stripes on its body, green tegmina with yellow spots, and pale red hind wings.</p>
<p class="pic-caption"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16875/pic_article_painted_grasshopper3.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>The wiki also mentions the interesting fact that these grasshoppers, when squeezed or handled, upon slight pinching of the head or abdomen, the half-grown immature form ejects liquid in a sharp and sudden jet, with a range of two inches or more, from a dorsal opening between the first and second abdominal segments. The discharge is directed towards the pinched area and may be repeated several times. The liquid is pale and milky, slightly viscous and bad-tasting, containing cardiac glycosides that the insect obtains from the plant it feeds upon.</p>
<p>Grasshoppers can eat their way rapidly through vegetation, being a veritable plague of locusts. They are plant-eaters, sometimes becoming serious pests of cereals, vegetables and pasture, especially when they swarm in their millions as locusts and destroy crops over wide areas.</p>
<p>Most grasshoppers are polyphagous, eating vegetation from multiple plant sources, but some are omnivorous and also eat animal tissue and animal faeces. In general their preference is for grasses, including many cereals grown as crops.</p>
<p>Grasshoppers seem extraordinarily sensitive to their environment through many of their senses. On the side of the head are a pair of large compound eyes which give a broad field of vision and can detect movement, shape, colour and distance. There are also three simple eyes (ocelli) on the forehead which can detect light intensity, a pair of antennae containing olfactory (smell) and touch receptors, and mouthparts containing gustatory (taste) receptors.</p>
<p>At the front end of the abdomen there is a pair of tympanal organs for sound reception. There are numerous fine hairs covering the whole body that act as mechanoreceptors (touch and wind sensors), and these are most dense on the antennae, the palps (part of the mouth), and on the cerci at the tip of the abdomen. There are special receptors (<em>campaniform sensillae</em>) embedded in the cuticle of the legs that sense pressure, too.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16876/pic_article_painted_grasshopper4.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>A large grasshopper such as a locust can jump about a metre (twenty body lengths) without using its wings! What a fascinating creature this is, and it was sheer chance that led me to this sighting, thanks to my friend Mani!</p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bengaluru inches towards a greener Ganesha festival</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/ramakanth-interview-ecofriendly-ganesha-festival-bangalore</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/ramakanth-interview-ecofriendly-ganesha-festival-bangalore</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2016 10:33:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>News Desk</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16846/small_clay_ganeshas.jpg" /><br/><p>Ganesha festival just got a bit more greener, with better awareness among communities in Bengaluru while more and more citizens went for ecofriendly Ganesha idols.</p>]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16846/small_clay_ganeshas.jpg" /><p>Eco-friendly Ganesha festival has caught up in a big way this year, in Bengaluru. Dedicated teams of volunteers have been struggling day and night, along with the Bruhat Bengaluru Mahanagara Palike (BBMP) and Karnataka State Pollution Control Board (KSPCB), to put proper disposal systems in place, and to spread awareness among people. Making one's own Ganesha using clay was the mantra for hundreds of citizens this year.</p>
<p>The result was obvious on the first day of the festival itself. According to Yatish Kumar K C, Additional Commissioner for BBMP West Zone, on the first daym there were 1350 clay Ganesha idols immrsed, as opposed to 400 PoP idols. Many other areas where volunteers were active reported similar trends where maximum Ganesha idols were made up of clay.</p>
<p>N S Ramakanth, a member of Solid Waste Management Round Table (SWMRT), who is one of the veteran eco-warriors of Bengaluru, says that out of the 1,27,000 Ganeshas immersed in Sankey Tank last year, 62,000 were clay Ganeshas, the rest, about 65,000, were made up of Plaster of Paris (PoP).</p>
<p>Ramakanth spoke to Priyanka, Radio Jockey of our Co-media Lab partner Radio Active 90.4 MHz Bangalore, on the issue. Listen to Ramakanth's interview here.</p>
<p><iframe src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/281316544&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false&amp;visual=true" frameborder="no" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="250"></iframe></p>
<p>PoP idols never dissolve in water - it's only metals that are in the idol that get dissolved, thereby polluting lake water. BBMP has made many arrangements and specific immersion points for the ecofriendly disposal of idols. Here's the list for all eight zones of BBMP. Click on it to enlarge the image.</p>
<p><a href="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16844/04_09_2016_008_008.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16844/pic_article_04_09_2016_008_008.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>
<p class="pic-caption">List of eco-friendly Ganesha immersion points in Bengaluru, released as an advertisement.</p>
<p>Unlike old days, there is better cordination among the BBMP these days, due to the advent of new age social media tools. Volunteers and BBMP officials have joined hands together and formed a WhatsApp group for festival waste management, which discusses and devises strategies to deal with all kinds of waste during all festivals, in every season, through the year.</p>
<p>During this Gowri-Ganesha festival, the group was very active, with volunteers and officials sharing information, directions and motivation in the group, and driving change in the waste management of the city during the festival. There was maximum promotion on social media for the cause, with awareness messages by everyone including the Chief Minister of the state. There have been many guidelines for the public by the BBMP on how to dispose of the idols and other waste.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16845/pic_article_guidelines.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">BBMP guidelines for Ganesha disposal.</p>
<p>However, the first round of Ganesha immersions happens from individual households and the bigger, community Ganeshas are disposed of little later. As community Ganeshas are bigger in size, the trend has been to go for Plaster of Paris idols, as there are not too many people who prepare big clay idols. Even this year, community Ganesha festival organisers were seen struggling to get information on where to buy big ecofriendy idols.</p>
<p>The final BBMP data on the number of idols immesed and the lake pollution data to be released by KSPCB to be released after all the immersions are over in the city will reveal the final picture of how ecofriendly the festival was.</p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New startups help farmers supply organic produce to Bengalureans</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/organic-farming-bangalore-movement</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/organic-farming-bangalore-movement</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 05:25:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Kate Clark</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<br/>New initiatives connect farmers and consumers - supplying fresh, chemical-free vegetables to Bengaluru residents.
]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[                <p>Why do I need to be eating a California apple? asks Laxminarayan Srinivasaiah, co-founder of <a href="http://jivabhumi.com/" target="_blank">Jivabhumi</a>, a new platform that connects local farmers to conscious consumers in Bengaluru.</p>
<p>Srinivasaiah and his two co-founders, left behind corporate stability earlier this year to fully commit to their growing business, which now feeds 600 Bengalureans. Their goal is twofold: to provide healthier, chemical-free, and locally-sourced food and to support farmers. Customers select the chemical-free local foods online, Jivabhumi works with local farmers and ships the food to local&nbsp;<a href="https://shop.jivabhumi.com/index.php?route=module/storepickup#content" target="_blank">pick-up points.</a></p>
<p>For now, Jivabhumi is targeting the conscious consumers, or those already aware of the benefits of organic farming and who can afford such products. Over the next few years they hope to reach and become more accessible to different populations.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17573/pic_article_jivabhumi.jpg" alt=""></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Visitors in a Jivabhumi farm. Pic: Jivabhumi Facebook page</p>
<p>The holy grail is only when food is made affordable to all consumers, says Sreenivasa Rao, another co-founder of Jivabhumi. We dont believe that organic food or naturally grown food should be available only to the elite customer. Unfortunately, that is the case today. Therefore, we are very consciously pricing our products... The idea of Jivabhumi really is how do you make it a win-win situation for both farmers as well as consumers.</p>
<h3>Nobody wants to be transparent in this business</h3>
<p>Rao explained the supply chain in India is very complex; by eliminating any middlemen, being entirely transparent, and working directly with farmers, Jivabhumi is simplifying the process and hopefully, improving the lives of farmers. Depending on the product, those in Jivabhumis 1300 plus farmer network get 50 to 70 percent of the profits, a stark increase to the 25 to 27 percent they say farmers typically get.</p>
<p>According to the National Sample Survey Office, the average income per agricultural household In India from 2012 to 2013 was Rs 6,426.</p>
<p>Nobody wants to be transparent in this business because unfortunately, the kind of profits that the retailers make is unbelievable, at the expense of beating the farmers down, Rao says. So nobody wants to be fair; thats where we really want to create that difference.</p>
<p>By eliminating the middlemen Jivabhumi is revealing the real price of food.</p>
<p>The normal reaction for people is why does organic cost so much, says Anil Nachig, co-founder of Jivabhumi. So, if you ask the question, what is the real price of food, you will realise the subsidised food, the cheap food coming in, is coming at a certain cost. The costs being environmental or socialsqueezing the farmer. Neither of these, Nachig explains, are sustainable, or beneficial to the local economy or ecosystem.</p>
<h3>Supporting farmers</h3>
<p>In the process of making food cheap and affordable to everyone, what are we doing? Srinivasaiah says. The farmer is being squeezed, right?</p>
<p>The negative impacts of <a href="http://www.worldbank.org/en/news/feature/2013/06/19/india-climate-change-impacts" target="_blank">climate change</a>, shrinking profits, and land, has led to a sharp decrease in the number of farmers in India over the last 20 years. <em>The Hindu </em>reported in 2013, that about <a href="http://www.thehindu.com/opinion/columns/sainath/over-2000-fewer-farmers-every-day/article4674190.ece" target="_blank">2,000 farmers</a> were leaving the profession every day, and that there were seven million fewer farmers in the country in 2013, than in 2001.</p>
<p>No one wants to do farming, Srinivasaiah says. Even if he has a farm, he is coming out of the farm and coming to Bangalore. He is fine to become a...security guard, he doesnt want to do farming because you have to depend on rains and if the rain doesnt come, how do you feed your family? Here if you become a security guard you have an income that you can look forward to at the end of the month.</p>
<p>Farmer suicides have also risen. Karnataka alone saw over <a href="http://www.deccanchronicle.com/current-affairs/130116/karnataka-breaks-record-1-002-farmers-ended-lives-this-fiscal.html" target="_blank">1,000 farmer deaths by suicide</a> from April 2015 to January 2016.</p>
<p>While the causes of the uptick in suicides are debated, the founders of Jivabhumi say if farmers are given a fair-trade, their standard of living will improve.</p>
<p>How do we make lives of the farmer better?Rao asks. The reason why a lot of them are moving out of this profession is simply because it is not profitable for them anymore. The reason again for that is that there is no fair-trade in the entire supply chain.</p>
<h3>More startups look at agriculture</h3>
<p><a href="http://www.organicmandya.com/" target="_blank">Organic Mandya</a>, an organic farmers society in Karnataka, caters to farmers in the Mandya district. Bengalureans can buy their organic products online, or at their store in Mandya.</p>
<p>Like Jivabhumi, they cut out the middlemen and started selling farmers organic products a year and a half ago. Today, in addition to selling food, they offer organic tourism, in hopes the question where does your food come from, can actually be answered by a growing population.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17574/pic_article_organic_mandya.jpg" alt=""></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Visitors and supporters of Organic Mandya can work in the farms connected with Organic Mandya. Pic: Organic Mandya FB page</p>
<p>Co-founder Bhaskara Kempaiah says there is definitely a growing demand for organic food. Take millets for example. Once less-popular, healthy alternatives to rice, millets are now in huge demand, according to both Kempaiah and Srinivasaiah of Jivabhumi.</p>
<p>Health is getting more important as people see their relatives struggling with health, Kempaiah says. He adds that organic farming can be more economical. Chemical-free farming eliminates the need to purchase the chemicals and pesticides usually used in farming. 10 to 15,000 rupees of input, if there is a disaster it's all lost, he says. With rain, they may end up losing all that money.</p>
<p>It can, however, take three to five years for the soil previously doused in pesticides to replenish, according to Srinivasaiah. That means there may be a period where farmers are producing a smaller than normal crop. The hope is the increase in payment farmers get by selling chemical-free food facilitates their ability to produce a smaller crop.</p>
<p>Another entrepreneur, Subeesh S is working on an enterprise that will similarly support farmers. His concept, '<a href="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/farmers-problems-solutions-from-cities" target="_blank">The Family Famer</a>'&nbsp;also removes middlemen, ensures farmers get a better cut of the profits, and that the food is chemical-free.</p>
<p>Subeesh says if farmers have a direct and personal relationship with the consumer, the consumer will get a better product and the farmer a better deal.</p>
<p>We all have a family doctor, whenever a problem comes he is the first consultant, Subeesh says. He[knows] all the history of the patient, similarly we[should have] a farmer, a family farmer.</p>
<h3>Live to eat or eat to live?</h3>
<p>All of these companies exist in part because of their passion to improve the lives of farmers, but they also want to see a healthier population in Bengaluru.</p>
<p>Everything boils down to the food on your plate, Sreenivasa Rao says. The question is...about the food choices you are making. Live to eat or eat to live?</p>

]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Bengaluru needs now: flood zone maps to help buyers</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/what-bengaluru-needs-now-flood-zone-maps-to-help-buyers</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/what-bengaluru-needs-now-flood-zone-maps-to-help-buyers</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Dr Ajaya S Bharadwaja</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<br/>t's not easy to navigate between loads of documents and see whether there is a violation in the property that you buy. Bengaluru needs to identify its flood zones to prevent future financial loss to the inhabitants.
]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17571/pic_article_remotemap.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Google Earth image from 2000 that shows a realistic view of elevation and valley in Kodichikkanahalli area.</p>
<p>Recent actions by the government to clear the drainage encroachments in the IT city have proved to be a tough incident both for the administration and to the individuals. Though people getting their plans approved or Khata documents can be attributed to the dark side of the administration as well as of the individual dweller, there are certain genuine innocent cases that are heart-breaking.</p>
<p>In the city considered to be IT capital of the country, where a normal cab driver reaches a completely unknown destination using a simple search in his smartphone, it is a pity that even so-called technically empowered professional of an IT firm is unable to figure out whether the location of the property he is planning to buy is an encroachment of lakebed or a drainage. That too, after spending months on research and consultation with real estate experts and lawyers.</p>
<p>Now that&rsquo;s a paradox. On one side we have the locational intelligence to the extent of navigating meter to meter that hardly consumes any time. On the other, even after researching for months together we fail to determine if a location falls within any specific zone. On the contrary we hear officials saying everyone must refer age old village maps before buying. Where did we go wrong?</p>
<p>In United States, which is highly prone for flooding disasters, for housing loan and construction purposes, it is mandatory that you obtain a certificate that specifies if the location of construction is within or outside the flood zone. In USA, the entire nation is divided into 500 years flood plain, 100 years floodplain and no floodplain. Depending on which zone the construction falls, the flood insurance is mandated and the premium is decided. Looks wow, but there is nothing special and similar project to decide encroachments is quite doable here as well.</p>
<h3><strong>Are we capable?</strong></h3>
<p>In fact we have already carried out better projects. BBMP has GIS maps with individual PIDs (Property IDs) for tax collection purpose. Here in this case, they have mapped each and every land parcel. This is quite time-consuming and tedious job. Coming up with flood-zoning maps is far simpler compared to GIS maps for individual PIDs. I am not really sure if the GIS maps for individual land parcels has helped in collecting taxes, but zoning maps will surely help in checking encroachment, corruption, confusion, cheating and eventually the unwanted incidents like demolition.</p>
<h3><strong>What do we have now?</strong></h3>
<p><a href="http://www.clearvalue.in/BDA.html">Clearvalue.in</a> is a website that has Bangalore CDP map overlaid on the satellite image. In the opening page one can select the area where the property lies and with an approximate idea of the location navigate to the area of interest and see in which zone of CDP the property lies. This gives a fair idea on if the property is likely to be in the danger zone. If the property is residential or mixed residential, yellow zone, with no green-coloured valley zone or storm water drains in between, the property is technically supposed to be safe.</p>
<p>This will give an idea on the zone in which the property is likely to fall. The overlaying on Clearvalue website is fairly accurate in the central part of the city and the accuracy fades as we move outside. Hence we can&rsquo;t take this as a tool to decide on buying a property. Hard copies of CDP will also be of not much use.</p>
<p>CDP is a comprehensive map of land use and land cover of an area, but many of the existing issues are not covered in the map. Also, we can&rsquo;t locate the property using the coordinates (latitude and longitude) of the property. This website is not authenticated by any government authority. The zoning can be checked by going to Drushti section of BDA website, however this section is offline most of the times.</p>
<p>Is this fool proof?</p>
<p>Absolutely not. The valley zones that are supposed to indicate flood zones in the CDP map are based on old village maps, but in reality many drains and lakes have been encroached and the topography of land changed. The CDP doesn&rsquo;t account for the realities caused by corruption and compulsion in the system.</p>
<h3><strong>A realistic view of flooding zones</strong></h3>
<p>What we need is a realistic view of the land and flooding. Primarily we need a GIS map of all the villages falling under the boundary of interest. A geo-referenced and mosaicked images of the villages can be used to digitise all the relevant features and also to classify them into different zones like government land, Rajakaluve, lake bed, public area etc. A zone where it is deemed that the construction is legal may be created for the easy understanding of the common man. Extreme care must be taken to ensure the accuracy of the maps.</p>
<p>Once this map is prepared, the existing GIS map of individual land parcels can be overlaid on this. Finally this combined maps can be overlaid on the satellite imagery for better visualisation. Transparency level of each layer must be allowed to be set by the user so that, it can be adjusted accordingly to be able to see the layer beneath.</p>
<p>Once the project goes live, the user should be able to locate the property by</p>
<ul>
<li>Navigating to the location by visual references</li>
<li>By entering the latitude and longitude of the property, which he can obtain by going to the site location using a smartphone (This would be the fool proof method of locating the property)</li>
</ul>
<p>If the property searched is falling within the zone where construction is legal in all means, the user can proceed to next step towards the purchase. If it is falling in other zones, where construction can&rsquo;t be permitted, it&rsquo;s a straight inference on the negative side. (Of course most of the constructions in east Bangalore would fall in red zone). This reduces the risk of the individual buyer that much. As the project would be carried out and approved by the government, officials or representatives will not be able to give any excuse on errors.</p>
<h3><strong>Do we have the expertise?</strong></h3>
<p>Very much. The government nodal agency for Remote Sensing and GIS, KSRSAC (Karnataka State Remote Sensing Application Centre) has proved its credentials beyond doubt, by successfully carrying out projects like LRIS (Land Resource Information System). Remote Sensing Centres of many states were waiting for the outcome of this project to carryout similar projects in their respective states. KSRSAC has set precedent in many such projects, which were far more complicate than the one we are talking about.</p>
<p>Budget and time consumed to complete the project would surely be less compared to the project of mapping individual land parcels.</p>
<p>Once complete and live, yes, an individual will be able use the locational intelligence to find if the property is genuine or encroached, as easily as he uses the locational intelligence for navigation in his smartphone. This is what this city and citizens need now, to prevent further disasters.</p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supreme Court asks states to take steps to save animals from plastic</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/supreme-court-order-on-plastic-ban-petition-by-karuna</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/supreme-court-order-on-plastic-ban-petition-by-karuna</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2016 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>News Desk</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<br/>                   http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/supreme-court-order-on-plastic-ban-petition-by-karuna    Karuna-Order-Asp          Document     Pages     Notes     Text             &nbsp;          Zoom   &nbsp;...]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<div id="DV-viewer-2997308-Karuna-Order-Asp" class="DV-container" style="position: relative; height: 800px;"><!--[if lte IE 8]><div class="DV-docViewer DV-clearfix DV-viewDocument DV-ie DV-autoZoom  DV-hideSidebar"><![endif]--> <!--[if (!IE)|(gte IE 9)]><!-->
<div class="DV-docViewer DV-clearfix DV-autoZoom  DV-hideSidebar DV-mini DV-supermini DV-viewDocument" style="position: absolute; top: 0px; bottom: 0px; left: 906px; right: 906px;"><!-- <![endif]-->
<div class="DV-docViewerWrapper">
<div class="DV-header">
<div class="DV-headerHat">
<div class="DV-branding"><span class="DV-storyLink">http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/supreme-court-order-on-plastic-ban-petition-by-karuna</span></div>
<div class="DV-title">Karuna-Order-Asp</div>
</div>
<div class="DV-controls">
<div class="DV-views">
<div class="DV-documentView DV-first"><span class="DV-trigger DV-selected">Document</span></div>
<div class="DV-thumbnailsView DV-last"><span class="DV-trigger">Pages</span></div>
<div class="DV-annotationView" style="display: none;"><span class="DV-trigger">Notes</span></div>
<div class="DV-textView" style="display: none;"><span class="DV-trigger">Text</span></div>
</div>
<div class="DV-collapsibleControls">
<div class="DV-searchBox DV-clearfix"><form class="DV-searchDocument" action="#" method="get">
<div class="DV-searchInputWrap">
<div class="DV-searchInput-cancel">&nbsp;</div>
<input class="DV-searchInput" type="text" /></div>
</form></div>
<div class="DV-zoomControls"><span class="DV-zoomLabel">Zoom</span>
<div class="DV-zoomBox ui-slider ui-slider-horizontal ui-widget ui-widget-content ui-corner-all">&nbsp;</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="DV-docViewer-Container">
<div class="DV-searchBarWrapper">
<div class="DV-searchBar"><span class="DV-trigger DV-closeSearch">CLOSE</span>
<div class="DV-searchPagination DV-foundResult">
<div class="DV-searchResults"><span class="DV-resultPrevious DV-trigger">Previous</span> <span> for &ldquo;&rdquo;</span> <span class="DV-resultNext DV-trigger">Next</span></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="DV-pages DV-hide-sidebar">
<div class="DV-paper">
<div class="DV-thumbnails">&nbsp;</div>
<div class="DV-pageCollection" style="width: 64px;">
<div class="DV-bar" style="height: 6552px;">&nbsp;</div>
<div class="DV-allAnnotations">&nbsp;</div>
<div class="DV-text">&nbsp;</div>
<div class="DV-set p0 DV-page-7 DV-loaded" style="top: -110px; left: 0px; height: 893px; width: 700px;" data-id="p0">
<div class="DV-overlay">&nbsp;</div>
<div class="DV-pageNoteInsert visible" title="Click to Add a Page Note">&nbsp;</div>
<div class="DV-pageMeta"><span class="DV-pageNumber">p. 7</span></div>
<div class="DV-annotations">&nbsp;</div>
<div class="DV-page" style="height: 863px; width: 700px;"><span class="DV-loading-top">Loading</span> <span class="DV-loading-bottom">Loading</span>
<div class="DV-cover">&nbsp;</div>
<img class="DV-pageImage" src="https://assets.documentcloud.org/documents/2997308/pages/Karuna-Order-Asp-p7-normal.gif" alt="" width="-36" height="-51" /></div>
</div>
<div class="DV-set p1 DV-loaded DV-page-2" style="top: -17px; left: 0px; height: 893px; width: 700px;" data-id="p1">
<div class="DV-overlay">&nbsp;</div>
<div class="DV-pageNoteInsert visible" title="Click to Add a Page Note">&nbsp;</div>
<div class="DV-pageMeta"><span class="DV-pageNumber">p. 2</span></div>
<div class="DV-annotations">&nbsp;</div>
<div class="DV-page" style="height: 863px; width: 700px;"><span class="DV-loading-top">Loading</span> <span class="DV-loading-bottom">Loading</span>
<div class="DV-cover">&nbsp;</div>
<img class="DV-pageImage" src="https://assets.documentcloud.org/documents/2997308/pages/Karuna-Order-Asp-p2-normal.gif" alt="" width="-36" height="-51" /></div>
</div>
<div class="DV-set p2 DV-loaded DV-page-6" style="top: -89px; left: 0px; height: 893px; width: 700px;" data-id="p2">
<div class="DV-overlay">&nbsp;</div>
<div class="DV-pageNoteInsert visible" title="Click to Add a Page Note">&nbsp;</div>
<div class="DV-pageMeta"><span class="DV-pageNumber">p. 6</span></div>
<div class="DV-annotations">&nbsp;</div>
<div class="DV-page" style="height: 863px; width: 700px;"><span class="DV-loading-top">Loading</span> <span class="DV-loading-bottom">Loading</span>
<div class="DV-cover">&nbsp;</div>
<img class="DV-pageImage" src="https://assets.documentcloud.org/documents/2997308/pages/Karuna-Order-Asp-p6-normal.gif" alt="" width="-36" height="-51" /></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="DV-sidebar">
<div class="DV-well">
<div class="DV-sidebarSpacer">&nbsp;</div>
<div id="" class="DV-navigation">
<div class="DV-description">
<div class="DV-descriptionHead">Karuna-Order-Asp</div>
</div>
<div class="DV-contentsHeader">Contents</div>
<div id="" class="DV-chaptersContainer" style="display: none;">&nbsp;</div>
<div class="DV-supplemental DV-noNavigation">
<div class="DV-storyLink"><a href="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/supreme-court-order-on-plastic-ban-petition-by-karuna" target="_blank">Related Article &raquo;</a></div>
<div class="DV-contributor">Contributed by: Shree DN, Citizen Matters</div>
</div>
<div class="DV-logo">&nbsp;</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="DV-footer">
<div class="DV-fullscreenContainer">&nbsp;</div>
<div class="DV-navControlsContainer">
<div class="DV-navControls DV-clearfix"><span class="DV-trigger DV-previous">&laquo;</span>
<div class="DV-clearfix DV-pageNumberContainer"><span class="DV-currentPagePrefix">Page</span> <span class="DV-currentAnnotationPrefix">Note&nbsp;</span> <span class="acceptInput-awaitingActivity"><span class="DV-currentPage">7</span><input class="acceptInput-textField" style="display: none;" type="text" /></span> <span class="DV-currentPageSuffix">of&nbsp; <span class="DV-totalPages">7</span> <span class="DV-totalAnnotations">0</span> </span></div>
<span class="DV-trigger DV-next">&raquo;</span></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="DV-printMessage">To print the document, click the "Original Document" link to open the original PDF. At this time it is not possible to print the document with annotations.</div>
<img class="DV-pixelping" src="//www.documentcloud.org/pixel.gif?key=document%3A2997308%3Ahttp%3A%2F%2Fwebcache.googleusercontent.com%2Fsearch" alt="" width="1" height="1" /></div>
</div>
<script type="text/javascript" src="//assets.documentcloud.org/viewer/loader.js"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="//assets.documentcloud.org/viewer/viewer.js"></script>
<script type="text/javascript">// <![CDATA[
DV.load("https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/2997308-Karuna-Order-Asp.js", {
  width: 600,
    height: 800,
    sidebar: false,
responsive: true,
    text: false,
    pdf: false,
    container: "#DV-viewer-2997308-Karuna-Order-Asp"
  });
// ]]]]><![CDATA[></script>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meet the vets of Bannerghatta Zoo</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/the-vets-of-bannerghatta-zoo</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/the-vets-of-bannerghatta-zoo</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2016 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<br/>Who takes care of the animals at Bengaluru's Bannerghata National Park what is their work like?
]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p class="p1">&ldquo;We were planning a trap for a tiger, waited for it and later realised that it was sitting atop a tree behind, watching us intently all the while.&rdquo; You may think this is a wildlife expert recounting his experience in the deep jungles. Not exactly. Dr Sujay, a senior vet at Bannerghata Biological&nbsp;Park, popularly known as the Bannerghata Zoo, has some fascinating stories of the animals in his care.</p>
<p class="p1"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17451/pic_article_bannerghatta.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Bannerghatta zoo. Pic: Saravana Bharathi</p>
<p class="p3">The <a href="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/1662-bannerghatta-zoo-wildlife-care" target="_blank">Bannerghata National Park</a> became an independent establishment in 2002. It&nbsp;includes the Zoo, Animal Safari, <a href="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/1702-bannerghatta-butterfly-park" target="_blank">Butterfly Park</a> and <a href="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/19-environment-animal-shelters-do-a-great-job-despite-odds-wildlife-rescue-and-rehabilitation" target="_blank">Rescue Center</a>.&nbsp;The Bannerghata zoo is a popular weekend visit, and children and adults alike visit it for a fun day out. But zoos play an even more important role, of helping the public learn about wildlife and conservation.</p>
<p class="p3">The people who make it possible are the zoo staff - the veterinarians and animal keepers. The almost&nbsp;invisible army operates round the clock to ensure a smooth functioning of the park - that the animals are taken well care of, and the public learns something new, and takes back memories of an enjoyable time.</p>
<p class="p3"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17452/pic_article_bbp1.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Bannerghatta Biological Park. Pic: Saravana Bharathi</p>
<p class="p1">The team of veterinarians is headed by Dr. Sujay, the Assistant Director of Veterinary Services. There are four veterinarians and one biologist. While the veterinarians focus on the physical aspect of the animals, the biologist focuses on the behavioural aspect of the animals. The daily routine of the veterinarians includes, going on rounds to monitor, testing the quality of the meat fed to the animals and treating their ailments. The biologist monitors the daily behaviour of animals, maintains the family tree and looks for symptoms of depression in the animals.</p>
<p>Two veterinarians reside inside the zoo quarters and the others live closeby. In a field that is quite challenging and not so financially rewarding, these doctors are driven by their passion. These doctors shared their unforgettable experiences as practitioners. One thing that was evident was their genuine love and passion for these animals they are taking care of.</p>
<h3><strong>Dr. Sujay, Assistant Director of Veterinary Services</strong></h3>
<p><strong><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17447/pic_article_sujayvet.JPG" alt="" /><br /></strong></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Dr Sujay. Pic: Saravana Bharathi</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We were planning a trap for a tiger, waited for it and later realised that it was sitting atop a tree behind, watching us intently all the while.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&nbsp;- <em>Dr. Sujay</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Dr. Sujay's love for nature and wildlife began when his dad, who was a professor in biology used to take him on nature trips. He shares his experiences in the wild, tranquillising wild animals and leaving them back in the forests.</p>
<p>Tranquillisation is challenging as the legs/arms of the animals have to be targeted where there is more muscle mass. If missed, the shot is as deadly as a bullet. He shares one instance, when he literally had to run away from a mad elephant that was further enraged because of the tranquilliser, "The effect of the tranquilliser starts to develop only after fifteen minutes. To be away from the animal in this sedation period is paramount for safety of oneself.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Yet another time, Sujay was planning to capture and confine a tiger to a fenced enclosure. The tiger never turned up and only later he realised that the tiger was watching them all the while, as they were planning the bait. &ldquo;The experience was chilling&rdquo;, he adds.</p>
<p>Under his supervision, the BBP boasts of housing one of the oldest surviving tigers in the world, Seetha. She once hurt herself in a trap kept for wild boars. The zoo hospital treated and nurtured her and she will soon enter the Guinness Book of Records as the oldest living tiger!</p>
<h3><strong>Message for the public: </strong>&nbsp;</h3>
<p><em>There is rampant littering in the premises of the zoo. Photography enthusiasts use flash excessively that disturb these animals. The public should be more particular about not disturbing the sanctity of the place and the creatures here.</em></p>
<h3><strong>Dr Nirupama Rao</strong></h3>
<p class="pic-caption"><strong><img style="margin-left: 6px; margin-right: 6px; float: left;" src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17446/pic_article_nirupamavet.JPG" alt="" width="383" height="272" /></strong>Dr Nirupama Rao. Pic: Saravana Bharathi</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;While treating lions, the protective cage opened suddenly. The lions could have hurt me. An intern watching this fainted. Luckily, I escaped.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&nbsp;- <em>Dr. Nirupama Rao</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The zoo is a second home to Dr Nirupama. She stays in the quarters and is always on her feet to treat the animals. She has been at Bannerghatta fo<strong>r</strong> six years now and each day is a new day for her. She is fond of the big cats.</p>
<p>Once she was treating two lions and the protective cage opened suddenly. In a very close encounter with the lions that could have cost her her life, she did not panic. One intern nearby fainted on the spot. She said, "I did not panic at the moment. I had to remain calm and composed."</p>
<p>The unperturbed lions spared her. She added, "every day is a new learning for me. We have to learn from our mistakes and make sure not to repeat them again."</p>
<p>She also mentioned another incident about Kasthuri, a tiger that was eating its own tail. She had to keep amputating the length of the tail to stop her. All the while Kasthuri was irritated and angry at her. Over a period of time, with her persistence in showering abundant love, Dr Nirupama managed to make friends with her. She added, &ldquo;Whenever I visit her at the Rescue Centre division of the park, she comes, sits near me and we talk. We talk to the animals. They talk back. One needs some compassion to understand the relationship&rdquo;, she ended.</p>
<h3><strong>Message for the public:&nbsp; </strong></h3>
<p><em>Feeding of animals upsets their appetite and puts them in depression. It is sad that even educated people feed the Zoo animals.</em></p>
<h3><strong>Dr. Nikitha</strong></h3>
<p class="pic-caption"><strong><img style="float: right; margin-left: 6px; margin-right: 6px;" src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17444/pic_article_vet3.jpg" alt="" width="383" height="381" /></strong></p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;The leopard I treat, gets irritated for a few minutes, but then starts to respond to my affection. Animals reciprocate what you show them, love or hatred. &ldquo;</p>
<p>&nbsp;- <em>Dr. Nikitha</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Dr. Nikitha is an avid lover of reptiles. Crocodiles are her favourite at the zoo. A nature lover since childhood, she decided to become a veterinarian. She worked in the Nagpur Jungle and the Pune Zoo before BBP.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Currently, I am treating a leopard. I treat her eyes four times a day in a squeeze cage. Every time I get close to her, she gets irritated for the first five minutes. She then forgives me, responds to my love and reciprocates. Animals pick cues from the body language of people around them and behave accordingly. The more you are kind and loving towards them, the more they will reciprocate the love you show them&rdquo;, she said.</p>
<h3><strong>Message for the public: </strong>&nbsp;</h3>
<p><em>People tease the animals in these enclosed spaces. They throw small stones at these creatures for their own entertainment and pleasure. Teasing is not restricted to children as adults too engage in this kind of a behaviour, many a times.</em></p>
<h3><strong>Dr. Puneeth Gowda</strong></h3>
<p><strong><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17442/pic_article_vet1.JPG" alt="" /><br /></strong></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Dr. Puneeth Gowda.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;We hide tablets inside rice balls to treat sick elephants. The intelligent ones would sniff and crush the rice balls and check for tablets before eating. Their intelligence is unmatched. &ldquo;</p>
<p>&nbsp;- <em>Dr. Puneeth Gowda</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Dr Puneeth Gowda though never actually planned to become a veterinarian now holds a PhD in Wildlife Diagnostics. He recollects the experience of monitoring a rare white tiger that gave birth to four cubs. Of the four cubs that were born, two cubs died soon enough. The responsibility of taking care of the mother and the remaining cubs was in his hands. He reminisces calling the caretakers regularly at night, making impromptu visits at wee hours and doing everything he could to ensure the well being of the cubs. Now, the hale and healthy cubs are four months old which he is really proud and happy about.</p>
<p>He also used to treat sick elephants by hiding tablets inside rice balls that were fed to them. &ldquo;The intelligent elephants would sniff and crush the rice balls to check for tablets, if any&rdquo;, he chuckled.</p>
<h3><strong>Message for the public: </strong>&nbsp;</h3>
<p><em>One main purpose of establishments of zoo is education and creating awareness. The zoo is an encyclopaedia in itself. I personally have seen parents wrongly educating their children about the names and species of animals. For example, leopards are mistaken for cheetahs and different species of monkeys are referred to as monkeys than by their specific names.</em></p>
<h3><strong>Mr. Kushal N, Biologist</strong></h3>
<p class="pic-caption"><strong><img style="margin-left: 6px; margin-right: 6px; float: right;" src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17448/pic_article_kushalvet.JPG" alt="" width="343" height="229" /></strong>Kushal N, Biologist Pic: Saravana Bharathi</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;I was studying the behaviour of a leopard for a year and a half. Finally, when it was captured and released into captivity, I was terribly upset that I had to part with the animal.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&nbsp;- <em>Kushal N</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Kushal is the only biologist at the Zoo. After speaking to some senior biologists at Bangalore Science Forum when he was in his teens, he decided to become a biologist. After years of volunteering, he is now at Bannerghatta, observing and understanding the behaviour of the animals. His duties include maintaining a family tree of different species of animals, checking their capabilities to reproduce, looking for symptoms of mental illness in animals, etc.</p>
<p>The observed symptoms are discussed with other doctors, caretakers and higher authorities to come to a conclusion on what the issue really is. Accordingly, the animals are treated.</p>
<p>Reminiscing a memorable experience, he mentioned, "while as a volunteer, I was observing a tiger for 1.5 years to understand its behaviour. Then it was captured and released into captivity. Parting from the animal made me terribly sad. In this profession, one really needs to maintain a balance between affection shown to the animals and the work that has to be done. The affection should not come in the way of duty."</p>
<h3><strong>Message for the public:</strong></h3>
<p><em>The animals in enclosed spaces are prone to get depressed. Any behaviour that would disturb these animals, should be avoided by the public.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>~~~</em></p>
<p><strong>The Assistant Director mentioned that the Zoo is in dire need of Volunteers who can spend quality time for the development of the zoo. People who are interested in volunteering can get the forms from the Bannerghatta Zoo hospital.</strong></p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tracing the wild animals of Bengaluru</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/tracing-the-wild-animals-of-bengaluru</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/tracing-the-wild-animals-of-bengaluru</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<br/> Every city, even a giant metropolis like Bengaluru, still has a few patches of green, blue or brown that have managed to survive or at least allay the formidable onslaught of concrete and glass. Look carefully in these oases and you&rsquo;ll be sure...]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p>Every city, even a giant metropolis like Bengaluru, still has a few patches of green, blue or brown that have managed to survive or at least allay the formidable onslaught of concrete and glass. Look carefully in these oases and you&rsquo;ll be sure to find a sign of life (or five)!</p>
<h3><strong>Snakes </strong></h3>
<p>Among the most revered and reviled animals in India, snakes are also very common in our cityscapes. Bengaluru has about 40 species of snakes of which six are venomous. Most snakes, even venomous ones, will flee upon detection. They only stand their ground when provoked or unable to escape. The rotting piles of garbage that we often dismiss as &ldquo;someone else&rsquo;s problem&rdquo; attract rodents, which in turn lure predators like snakes.</p>
<p>Thus, as a result of surprise encounters with snakes, India suffers one million snakebites a year with about 50,000 fatalities reported. The only solution to symptoms of snakebite from a venomous snake is the administration of anti-venom, available at government hospitals. Snake repellents, mantras and other such remedies are ineffective.</p>
<h3><strong>Bats</strong></h3>
<p>Bats are flying mammals who rest in crevices of rocks, buildings and in the canopies of trees. While bats aren&rsquo;t blind, they navigate using echolocation (i.e., they send out sound waves and listen for echoes that bounce off objects, including prey). Bengaluru has about 25 to 30 species of bats. The most known are the flying fox and the common pipistrelle. Flying foxes are named for their fox-like appearance, they feed on fruits, and thus aid in pollination and seed dispersal. Pipistrelles can be found hovering around lamp posts, hawking insects on the wing. Bats are threatened by habitat modification and destruction. For example, the fate of an entire colony of bats near Bengaluru&rsquo;s Sankey tank hangs in the balance owing to developmental activities.</p>
<h3><strong>Jackals</strong></h3>
<p>A jaunt near a lakebed, scrubland or agricultural area may bring you face-to-face with the dog-like creature trotting on spindly legs. Traditional lore maligns them as sly and cunning. But jackals are actually furtive animals who have masterfully adapted to their shrinking habitats thanks to their ability to remain discreet. Jackals are primarily scavengers, but are known to take birds, rodents and other small mammals, too. Feisty survivors they may be, they are still threatened by habitat loss, poaching for skin and meat and for pet trade. Some people keep jackals in captivity due to the belief that they bestow good luck.</p>
<h3><strong>Slender loris</strong></h3>
<p>Keen eyes, patience and a dash of luck will help you make an acquaintance with an interesting arboreal primate with large limpid eyes that shine a brilliant orange under a flashlight. The slender loris or Kadoo Papa (i.e., &lsquo;baby of the forest&rsquo; in Kannada) is a nocturnal animal and can be found lurking in tree tops. In denying this creature any proclivity for speed, nature has enabled him to creep up to his prey with enviable stealth. With his voracious appetite for insects, this primate serves as an excellent system of pest control, especially in and around farmlands. Apart from habitat loss, the slender loris faces persecution from humans who use him to exact revenge on their enemies, based on the superstition that inflicting an injury on the animal will result in the same injury in one&rsquo;s enemy.</p>
<h3><strong>Jungle cat</strong></h3>
<p>When T S Eliot wrote of Macavity, the gravity defying, levitating cat, he could have been speaking of the jungle cat. Found on the fringes of scrublands and other areas with moderate vegetation, this golden-brown cat takes due advantage of her inborn speed and dexterity to stalk prey such as quick-moving birds, reptiles and rodents, as well as to escape predators who are unfamiliar with her quick-footedness.</p>
<p>They eschew the mewling of their domestic cousins for a low pitched purr or growl. This cat&rsquo;s ability to adapt to an ever-shrinking habitat is a lesson of resilience. However, there is a need for greater tolerance on the part of human beings who injure or kill these animals when they &lsquo;stray&rsquo; into human habitation.</p>
<p>Consider this a tiny introduction to the fascinating forms of life that are all around you. Observing the wildlife in your backyard can open up a gateway to the natural world. For it is only when you engage with nature that you will want to defend it.</p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clearing the drains before the rains: a pictorial how-to guide!</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/clearing-the-drains-before-the-rains-a-pictorial-how-to-guide</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/clearing-the-drains-before-the-rains-a-pictorial-how-to-guide</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2016 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Tara Krishnaswamy</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<br/>A team of citizens cleared rainwater channels and helped rainwater flow into the lake. Here's how they did it. ]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p>I needed that drink after just an hour out in the sun on Saturday morning near the Puttenahalli Lake, at Nataraj Layout in JP Nagar.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17199/pic_article_natraj-frooti.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>More labour under what looked like a deceptively dull sky that morning and it quietly saps you.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17200/pic_article_natraj-vols.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>At that point, all resolutions incinerate instantly and the body rejects what appears like salad, fresh though it may be.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17201/pic_article_natraj-salad.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>Instead, the body wants to chill on a mat,</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17202/pic_article_natraj-mat.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>or even better, on a seat</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17208/pic_article_natraj_seat.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>with liquid much stronger.</p>
<p>And voila! Nothing like the kind consideration of my fellow nationals in the thoughtful accompaniment of the glass with the bottle.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17203/pic_article_natraj-drink.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>A bit more clearing and 30% calorie and salts lost must be compensated</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17204/pic_article_natraj-vols-dig.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>and not to mention, the stronger brew is sad and lonely without munchies.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17205/pic_article_natraj-kurkure.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>As time wears on, one is inevitably drained and no mat-in-drain or slab-in-drain can compete with the irresistible beckoning of the beanie-in-drain.</p>
<p><br /><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17206/pic_article_natraj-beanbag.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>Dhanyavadagalu aplenty to the regurgitating earth of Namma Bengaluru for its boundless generosity and tolerance that we've mercilessly stripped. A hygiene conscious citizenry that we are, it's time to wash up and scram with the treasures before we're caught with muddy hands.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17207/pic_article_natraj-soap.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>You can only lament, "Ayyo, the treasures of the storm water khazana of Nataraj Layout have been mined by selfish volunteers and BBMP personnel, and we will be left with nothing but rain water running with impunity to the lake. <em>En, appa idi?</em>&rdquo;</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/17209/pic_article_natraj_sit.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>Our repartee, "<em>Swalpa adjust maad bidi!</em>"</p>
<p>PS: A &ldquo;cut&rdquo; of the treasure has been sent off to the Sutradhari, Srinivas Alavilli, who gave us the blueprint for this "<a href="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/let-s-send-some-rainwater-to-our-lakes-in-bengaluru" target="_blank">daylight robbery</a>".</p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Green tribunal allows construction on Kaikondrahalli lake wetland</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/green-tribunal-allows-construction-on-kaikondrahalli-lake-wetland</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/green-tribunal-allows-construction-on-kaikondrahalli-lake-wetland</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2016 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Akshatha M</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<br/><p>National Green Tribunal has allowed the developer to construct the residential project, after the developer modified the project plan by reducing the extent of construction.</p>]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16880/pic_article_pic_article_1.png" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Difference between the topography of the land between Kasavanahalli and Kaikondrahalli lakes, in 2002 and 2016, as seen on Google Earth.</p>
<p>The Southern Bench of National Green Tribunal has dismissed the petition of Namma Bengaluru Foundation (NBF) and Mahadevpura Parisara Samrakshane Mattu Abhivrudhi Samiti (MAPSAS) related to a residential project coming up between Kasavanahalli and Kaikondarahalli lakes.</p>
<p>Stating that the case on the grounds that the developer has a valid Environmental Clearance, the NGT dismissed the petition and allowed the developer of Shriram Chirping Woods to continue with the project.<br />In an order delivered on April 26th, NGT bench comprising Dr P Jyothimani and P S Rao, dismissed the original application as well as the appeal made by the appellant. The court observed that according to the modified project plan approved by SEIAA, the project was coming up in a plot area of 62,927 sq metres, with a reduction of 1,112.07 sq metres from the original plan.</p>
<p>The modified plan intends to construct 17 towers with 810 residential units as against 21 towers and 870 residential units in the previous project plan. The NGT observed that the plan was modified to avoid the nala passing through the property. &ldquo;It can not be said there has been any violation which substantially affects the original Environmental Clearance granted to the project proponent,&rdquo; the court said.</p>
<p>Responding to the demands of the applicant&rsquo;s counsel to consider the secondary rajakaluve running between the two lakes as primary rajakaluve, the court said that according to BDA RMP, the canal is a secondary canal and a minimum of 25 metres buffer zone has to be left out on both sides. The BDA has clarified that there has been no encroachment of Rajakaluve between Kasavanahalli and Kaikondarahalli lakes, the NGT bench observed.</p>
<p>However the court warned the developer not to disturb the course of Rajakaluve in future and in such case it will be always open before SEIAA to take action against the developer.</p>
<p><em>Citizen Matters</em> had earlier written about the project, and had sought plans from the developer with regard to the drain in the valley zone, but had received no reply. Meanwhile, there is yet another construction coming up on the lake buffer zone in the wetland between Kaikondrahalli and Kasavanahalli lakes. Residents are concerned because these two lakes are interconnected with water from one lake flowing to another, and disturbing the flow pattern might affect the water inflow to the Kaikondrahalli lake.</p>
<h3>Full order of National Green Tribunal:</h3>
<p style="margin: 12px auto 6px auto; font-family: Helvetica,Arial,Sans-serif; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; font-size: 14px; line-height: normal; font-size-adjust: none; font-stretch: normal; -x-system-font: none; display: block;">Source: <a style="text-decoration: underline;" title="National" href="/web/20160503122829/http://www.greentribunal.gov.in/Writereaddata/Downloads/175-2015%28SZ%29OA-JUG-26-4-2016.pdf">National Green Tribunal</a></p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>870-unit realty project helping kill lake wetlands off Sarjapura Road</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/870-unit-realty-project-helps-kill-the-wetlands-between-two-lakes</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/870-unit-realty-project-helps-kill-the-wetlands-between-two-lakes</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2016 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Akshatha M</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<br/><p>The BDA and Environmental Clearance Committees sanctioned this project on the wetlands between Kasavanahalli and Kaikondrahalli lakes. Expert studies say it will affect the lakes. With residents opposing, case is on in the National Green Tribunal.</p>]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p>City planning authorities who often come under fire for their decisions, are facing yet another accusation this time, for sanctioning a mega development project in an ecologically sensitive area. BDA has approved a private residential project in an area comprising valley and buffer zones in Varthur Hobli, while State Environment Impact Assessment Authority (SEIAA) and Karnataka State Pollution Control Board (KSPCB) have issued the environmental clearances.</p>
<p>The residential project - Shriram Chirping Woods by Shrivision Homes Pvt Ltd - is under construction in an ecologically sensitive area between Kasavanahalli (Harlur) and Kaikondarahalli lakes in <a href="/web/20160426120557/https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/2805325-Shriram-BDA-Survey-Numbers.html" target="_blank">Varthur hobli</a>. The area is a wetland located in the downstream of Kasavanahalli lake and upstream of Kaikondrahalli lake.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16879/pic_article_pic_article_valley.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Valley zone as per BDA's Revised Master Plan, clearly demarcating the valley zone and the nala.</p>
<p>According to <a href="/web/20160426120557/http://clearvalue.in/cdp/cdpMap.html?Srch=Harlur,%20Bengaluru,%20Karnataka,%20India&amp;Type=BDA" target="_blank">Revised Master Plan 2015</a>, a secondary drain (Nala buffer) runs through the project property flowing from Kasavanahalli lake to Kaikondarahalli lake. While the area with nala is in valley zone, the surrounding area had been classified as &lsquo;Industrial Hi-tech zone&rsquo; with purple colour.</p>
<p>Shriram Homes Pvt Ltd had filed an application with BDA for change of land use for the project in 2012. Shriram had requested BDA to make change of land use for the project area of 15 acre 33 gunta, from Industrial Hi-tech to Residential and exclude certain portion of the property from valley zone.</p>
<h3>BDA not so sensitive about sensitive zone</h3>
<p>The BDA, in a letter dated January 9, 2013 mentions that in the total project property, 7 acre 6.48 gunta falls within the sensitive zone, 1 acre 38 gunta falls within the buffer zone and 1 acre 1.25 guntas is the estimated land required for the road construction. As 7 acre of the project area falls under sensitive valley zone, BDA did not directly grant the permission, but <a href="/web/20160426120557/https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/2805327-BDA-Doc-Refer-to-Sub-Committee.html" target="_blank">referred</a> the application to its Sensitive Zone Sub-Committee. &nbsp;</p>
<p>The <a href="/web/20160426120557/https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/2805328-BDA-Doc-Sub-Committee.html" target="_blank">Sub-Committee</a> which inspected the project property, granted permission for change of land use based on some <a href="/web/20160426120557/https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/2805326-BDA-Change-of-Land-Conditions.html" target="_blank">terms and conditions</a>. The Committee recommended that a buffer zone of 25 metres should be earmarked on both sides of secondary nala buffer connecting Kasavanahalli and Kaikondarahalli lakes. Further, it imposed another condition that, all other Rajakaluves existing in the project property should be demarcated and no construction should be allowed there and no untreated water should be flown out.</p>
<p>It also recommended a study of the water table, before constructing basements. Proper arrangements for water to flow into valley region, planting of trees in the buffer zone of the valley, were the other conditions. With these, the committee removed the &ldquo;sensitive&rdquo; clause from the land use of the valley.</p>
<p>Alongwith this, a BDA document shows that the position of the nala was changed in the survey map.</p>
<p><a href="/web/20160426120557/http://bbmp.gov.in/documents/10180/504904/Zoning_Regulations_RMP2015f.pdf/0a916060-b198-4903-b7cd-d18db7096ebd#40" target="_blank">RMP 2015</a>, says that <em>any valley for which permission has been accorded either by the authority or government, then such permission will be valid irrespective of the land use classification in the RMP 2015</em>. Fresh permissions shall not be accorded in valley zone. However, the permission for this project was given in 2013.</p>
<p>Once the change of land use was done, the builder applied for the development plan sanction. BDA sanctioned development plan for Shriram Chirping Woods in May 2013. The plan was <a href="/web/20160426120557/https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/2805324-BDA-Shriram-Project-Plan.html" target="_blank">sanctioned</a> with certain terms and conditions.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16880/pic_article_pic_article_1.png" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Difference between the topography of the land between Kasavanahalli and Kaikondrahalli lakes, in 2002 and 2016, as seen on Google Earth.</p>
<p>\Some of the conditions were:</p>
<ul>
<li>The project proponent should relinquish and develop 100 metres of land on either side of the project property for road widening</li>
<li>The project should not use the area for the purposes not specified in the land use.</li>
<li>Sewage treatment plant should be constructed with permission from BWSSB. Solid Waste Management should also have required facilities. There should be dual plumbing system in the buildings constructed to make use of the treated water.</li>
<li>10 per cent of the villas/apartments should be reserved for Economically Weaker Section of society and lower income groups.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Original plan and the modified plan</h3>
<p>Subsequently, the developer filed for Environmental Clearance and Consent for Establishment from State Environment Impact Assessment Authority (SEIAA) and Karnataka State Pollution Control Board (KSPCB), respectively. In May 2013, they got <a href="/web/20160426120557/http://kspcb.gov.in/Mayconsent.pdf" target="_blank">Consent for Establishment</a> form KSPCB, and in July 2013 they got <a href="/web/20160426120557/http://seiaa.kar.nic.in/Construction/con%20%20ec%20issued%20datewise/con-2013/2013/3%20CON%202013%20Shrivision%20Homes%20Pvt.%20Ltd.pdf" target="_blank">Environmental Clearance</a> from State Environment Impact Assessment Authority (SEIAA).</p>
<p>The Environment Clearance from SEIAA states that the project plot area is 64,039.81 sq metres and it will have 21 towers, up to 16 floors each, totalling 870 units. The EC clearly mentions that the permitted height is 44.93 meters, and in case of any change in the scope of the project, the project would require a fresh appraisal by the Authority.</p>
<p>However, the developer modified the project plan and an application was submitted to BDA in December 2013. According to the modified plan sanction issued in June 2014, the project comprises of 3 blocks with 870 residential units. Block 1 will have a residential building of 2 BF+G+19 floors and Basement+G+1 multi-purpose hall. In Block 2 - Tower 1 = Basement+G+19, Tower 2, 3 and 4 = 2 Basement+G+24 and 2 Basement+G+1 Club house. Block 3 will have G+6 and 1 floor club house.</p>
<p>The height of the apartment is now 76 metres and the project area is spread over 61,612 sq metres. In addition, the developer also proposed to utilise rajakaluve buffer zone as park and open space.</p>
<p>Though the developer applied for fresh EC and Consent for Establishment in November 2014, they did not get the EC till recently. KSPCB issued Consent of Establishment in February 2015, whereas SEIAA granted Environment Clearance to the project (modified plan) only in December 2015. While issuing the Environmental Clearance, the SEIAA has put some specific conditions on the developer to be followed during construction phase.</p>
<p>The conditions include -</p>
<ul>
<li>setting up an environment management cell to manage and maintain all environmental aspects</li>
<li>appointing an environment and safety engineer during the construction phase to ensure no noise nuisance, air and water pollution is caused</li>
</ul>
<p>Surprisingly, SEIAA <a href="/web/20160426120557/http://seiaa.kar.nic.in/Construction/LIST%20OF%20CONSTRUCTION%202014.html" target="_blank">website</a> continues to show the status of the EC application for Shrivision Homes Pvt Ltd as &ldquo;being considered by SEAC.&rdquo;</p>
<h3><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16881/pic_article_pic_article_Valley_dug.jpg" alt="" /></h3>
<p class="pic-caption">A photo taken in January 2014, showing how water seeped out from the ground when the wetland was being dug for forming the foundation.</p>
<h3>&lsquo;Wetland crucial for the survival of Kaikondrahalli lake&rsquo;</h3>
<p>There are certain reasons behind why the project has caused worry in a growing city like Bengaluru where development is taking place at the cost of environment. Study reports by professors at the Indian Institute of Science and Azim Premji University have cautioned against how construction at wetlands would harm the ecology.</p>
<p>A report on &ldquo;Ecological and environmental importance of the wetland upstream of Kaikondarahalli lake, the site of proposed Shriram Chirping Woods Project,&rdquo; was prepared by Prof Harini Nagendra, from School of Development at Azim Premji University, in November 2014.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16882/pic_article_pic_article_construction.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Construction going on in the wetland area. Pic: Reclaim Bengaluru team</p>
<p class="pic-caption"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16883/pic_article_pic_article_debris.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Construction going on in the wetland area. Pic: Reclaim Bengaluru team</p>
<p>The study explains the process of Kaikondarahalli lake restoration by BBMP and how the lake has become a model for participatory community-led lake restoration in Bengaluru city.</p>
<p>It highlights how the entire wetland between Kasavanahalli and Kaikondarahalli lakes, which is a low lying area, is flooded with water appearing like a large shallow lake during monsoon. &ldquo;The village map of Kasavanahalli indicates the presence of two kaluves in this wetland, which channel water into Kaikondrahalli lake. It is critical to survey, demarcate and protect these kaluves from being built over. The wetland area is also vital for replenishing the lakes downstream of Kasavanahalli, i.e. Kaikondrahalli, and Sowlkere. Disruptions of flow in an upstream lake lead to disastrous consequences on downstream lakes, as Bengaluru has witnessed over the past several years,&rdquo; the report says.</p>
<div class="middle-column-special-box-right"><strong>Facts about the project in a nutshell:</strong>
<ul>
<li>BDA made change of land use from Industrial Hi-Tech to Residential on February 5th, 2013</li>
<li>BDA sanctioned development plan on May 15th, 2013.</li>
<li>Environmental Clearance from SEIAA on July 29th, 2013</li>
<li>Developer applies for sanction of a modified development plan with BDA on December 6th, 2013.</li>
<li>The modified plan proposes to utilise the rajakaluve buffer zone as a park and open space and change the course of the Rajakaluve running through the project area, to another location within the project area.</li>
<li>BDA sanctions the modified plan on June 24th, 2014. In the sanction plan BDA says that the developer can change the course of Rajakaluve but is subject to the approval of BBMP.</li>
<li>SEIAA grants fresh Environmental Clearance on December 8th, 2015.</li>
<li>The project will have 810 residential units in 17 towers.</li>
<li>Parking space is for 1,237 cars.</li>
<li>Total water consumption is 561 KLD</li>
</ul>
</div>
<h3>&lsquo;Valley zones are no-development zones&rsquo;</h3>
<p>The Indian Institute of Science has published <a href="/web/20160426120557/https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/2805231-IISC-ETR85-KAIKONDANAHALLI.html" target="_blank">ENVIS Technical Report</a> in January 2015, titled &ldquo;Vanishing lakes interconnectivity and violations in valley zone: Lack of coordination among para-state agencies.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The report highlights the sad state of affairs of Kaikondarahalli and Kasavanahalli lakes. The reports says, &ldquo;the fresh sewage entering in south side of Kasavanahalli lake and a drainage channel is being destroyed due to construction activities that are taking place on the lake bed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The report states that construction activities in valley zone are contrary to sustainable development as the natural resources get affected. Eventually this kills the lake. Valley zones are no development zones as per CDP 2005 and 2015.</p>
<p>In case of highrise buildings in flood prone zone of the lake, a 30-metre buffer of &ldquo;no development zone&rdquo; is to be maintained. Removal of Rajakaluve or lake connectivity enhances episodes of flooding and associated disasters and affects ground water in the region.</p>
<p>On land use changes, the report says the conversion of green over/vegetation in the watershed especially in the valley zone regions of the lake to paved surfaces would alter the hydrological regime leading to flash floods, lowered groundwater table, less water in the lake during lean seasons.</p>
<h3>Battle on in the Green court</h3>
<p>In an attempt to save the lake, citizens of Bengaluru have approached the Southern Bench of National Green Tribunal questioning the construction activities at valley zone between Kaikondarahalli and Kasavanahalli lakes. Namma Bengaluru Foundation (NBF) and Mahadevapura Parisara Samrakshane Mathu Abhivruddhi Samiti (MAPSAS) filed a litigation in NGT in October 2015, questioning the project. The applicants in their original application had contended that the project is developed in an ecologically sensitive area, hence would harm the environment.</p>
<p>They also held that the authorities had given permission to the project without application of mind and without assessing the environmental damage that the project would cause.</p>
<p>The NGT, in its interim order on October 26th, 2015, granted a stay restraining Shrivision Homes Pvt Ltd from carrying on construction work in the project area until further orders.</p>
<p>Later the developers filed their reply to the order and requested the court to vacate the stay. The Tribunal in its <a href="/web/20160426120557/http://www.indiaenvironmentportal.org.in/files/Kasavanahalli%20Lake%20housing%20project%20NGT%20order.pdf" target="_blank">order</a> dated February 8th, 2016 vacated the stay and allowed the construction of six other floors in the first tower where 10 floors are already constructed, till the next orders.</p>
<p>The NGT bench in its order observed that the applicants have not chosen to challenge either the permission granted by BDA or the clearances issued by SEIAA and KSPCB, but only sought to restrain the construction activities.</p>
<p>Based on the NGT observations, one of the petitioners submitted an appeal last month. Here, the applicant has accused the developer of starting the construction work prior to obtaining environmental clearance from SEIAA for the revised project plan. SEIAA granted EC to the developer for the revised project only in December 2015, when the case was before the NGT. The appellant has pointed that the SEIAA issued certificate when the case was in the court and did not taken any action against the developer.</p>
<p>The appellant pointed to the discrepancy in the certificates issued by SEIAA and KSPCB with a clear difference in built-up area and has accused the developer of suppressing facts before the authorities. The Namma Bengaluru Foundation (NBF) has also expressed its concern over how shifting of rajakaluve running through the property would affect the water flow.</p>
<p>The matter is pending before the NGT. <em>Citizen Matters</em> wrote to the project proponents asking for a clarification on the steps taken to have the nala intact and/or mitigate the flooding. We are yet to receive a reply. The article will be updated if and when we receive a reply.</p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NGO wants to plant 60,000 saplings in Karnataka in 41 days</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/an-ngo-that-wants-to-plant-60-000-saplings-in-karnataka-in-41-days</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/an-ngo-that-wants-to-plant-60-000-saplings-in-karnataka-in-41-days</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>News Desk</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<br/>Imagine cycling through the length and breadth of Karnataka? That's exactly what this NGO wants to do. And while they are at it, they want to plant 60,000 saplings across the state.]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p>enter for Education Environment and Community, in partnership with <a href="https://www.facebook.com/profile.php?id=100011621222643" target="_blank">Cycle For Cause</a>, is organising a cycle rally, to celebrate World Earth Day and World Environment Day.</p>
<p>Kicking off from Bengaluru on Earth Day, which falls on April 22nd, the group hopes to cover 30 district headquarters in Karnataka, including places in North Karnataka like Bidar, Raichur and Gulbarga, before returning to Bengaluru on World Environment Day, which falls on June 5th.</p>
<p>During the course of the trip, the group is looking to promote reforestation by engaging with local organisations, colleges, individuals and government departments. The plan is to plant 60,000 saplings across all district headquarters in the period between Earth Day and World Environment Day. This is part of the larger plan to plant&nbsp;7.8 billion trees by 2020.</p>
<p>Other activities that will be conducted during the course of the rally include:&nbsp;</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Mobilising 20,000 cyclists in Karanataka Parade in Bangaluru on World Environment Day</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Planting 60,000&nbsp;samplings in all district headquarters&nbsp;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Promoting and encouraging cycling for sports and environment</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Cycling Safety Awareness programs</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Promoting treated wastewater reuse for gardening and avenue plantation</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Promoting the use of solar power for homes, buildings, transportation, and entire cities</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Explore opportunities to improve and expand sustainable public transportation networks&nbsp;</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>To participate in the rally, and for more information, you can reach out to Dr Hariesh on 93413 90529&nbsp;or Sunil KG on 99162 38377.</p>
<h3>Tentative route</h3>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16878/pic_article_route_map.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Bangalore - April 22, 2016 - 50 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ramanagara - April 23, 2016 - 60 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Mandya - April 24, 2016 - 45 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Mysore - April 25, 2016 - 70 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Chamarajanagara - April 26, 2016</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Madikeri - April 28, 2016 - 140 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>DK - Mangalore - April 30, 2016 - 180 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Hassan &ndash; May 02, 2016 &ndash; 60 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Chikmagalur - May 03, 2016 - 120 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Sivamogge - 05 june 2016- 120 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Davanagere - May 6, 2016 - 75 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Haveri &ndash; May 7, 2016 - 80 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Gadag &ndash; May 8, 2016- 65 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Dharward &ndash; 9 May 2016 - 80 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Dandeli (Uttara Kannada)&ndash; 10 May 2016</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Belgaum - 10 May 2016 - 80 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Chikkodi - May 11, 2016 -140 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Bijapur - 13 May 2016 - 160 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Gulbarga -15 May 2016- 120 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Bidar - 17 May 2016 - 180 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Yadgir - 20 May 2016 - 85 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Raichur - 21 May 2016- 200 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Bagalkote- 24 may 2016 &ndash; 110 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Koppal - 26 May 2016- 180 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Bellary - 28 May 2016 - 140 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Chitradurga - May 30, 2016 - 90 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Tumakuru &ndash; May 31, 2016- 100 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Chikkaballapura &ndash; 02 June 2016 - 60 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Kolar &ndash; 03 June 2016 - 70 km</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Bangalore Rural &ndash; 04 June 2016</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Bangalore &ndash; 05 June 2016 &ndash; World Environment Day</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3>About Center for Education Environment and Community</h3>
<p>Center for Education Environment and Community (CEECo) is a registered non-for-profit organisation working in the areas of activity-based environmental education, community-based environmental conservation and rural development from 2009. Since its inception, the organisation has been working to create a healthy and sustainable environment. It believes that a healthy environment is one which has healthy people.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ceeco.co.in/" target="_blank">www.ceeco.co.in</a></p>
<h3>About CycleforCause</h3>
<p>CycleforCause is an initiative floated by like-minded cyclists with an intent to provide a platform to empower cycling communities, prospective cyclists, and sensitising them about environment pollution.</p>
<p>CycleforCause is&nbsp;an initiative floated by like-minded cyclists with an intent to provide a platform to empower cycling communities, prospective cyclists, and sensitising them about environment pollution.</p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No studies, no data: air pollution continues to haunt Bengaluru</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/no-studies-no-data-air-pollution-continues-to-haunt-bengaluru</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/no-studies-no-data-air-pollution-continues-to-haunt-bengaluru</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Navya P K</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<br/>Anecdotes and basic studies show air pollution causes lung diseases in Bengaluru. But, nobody is collecting the data that can support strong measures to curb pollution. ]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<div class="article-body" style="border-top: none;">
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16037/pic_article_pollution.jpg" alt="pollution in Bengaluru" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Pic: Mayur Channagere</p>
<p>If you are someone who rides a bike for more than four hours in Bengaluru every day, there&rsquo;s a significant chance that you will develop Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD). COPD, which makes breathing difficult, is a leading cause of disability and death globally; it is irreversible and worsens over time.</p>
<p>The conclusion is from a <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/279868491_Susceptibility_Of_Chronic_Obstructive_Pulmonary_Disease_Among_Bike_Riders_In_Bangalore_Using_Bode_Index" target="_blank">study</a> on 100 non-smokers in Bengaluru aged 25-40 years, who commute to work by bike. Given the worsening traffic jams in the city, the number of people riding bikes for over four hours per day could be quite high.</p>
<p>But respiratory diseases like COPD are not the only risks from air pollution. Many global studies have shown that air pollution can cause many non-communicable diseases (NCDs) like heart diseases, stroke, lung cancer, low birth weight and congenital disorders like cleft palate. For example, a recent<a href="http://www.bmj.com/content/bmj/350/bmj.h1295.full.pdf" target="_blank"> review</a> of studies between 1990 and 2014 from 28 countries showed that stroke-related deaths and hospitalisations were closely linked with air pollution, and that the correlation was strongest in low and middle income countries.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16879/pic_article_mask.jpg" alt="pollution mask" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Pictures of a cyclist's mask - before and after the use. Pic: Akshay Yadav</p>
<p>Some other studies have shown air pollution's correlations with <a href="http://www.downtoearth.org.in/coverage/no-escape-14375" target="_blank">lung cancer and heart diseases</a>,<a href="http://www.downtoearth.org.in/news/air-pollution-now-shown-to-impact-a-gene-associated-with-alzheimer-s-disease-51418" target="_blank"> Alzheimer&rsquo;s disease</a>, <a href="http://ehp.niehs.nih.gov/1409546/" target="_blank">low birth weight and smaller head circumference in newborns</a> etc. Children are more at risk, and could suffer lasting health impacts. Elderly are also more vulnerable because of their weaker immune system.</p>
<p>Here is a personal story of a cyclist from the city of Bengaluru.</p>
<p><iframe style="border: 1px solid #CCC; border-width: 1px; margin-bottom: 5px; max-width: 100%;" src="//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/jdE3844SG9jOB" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" width="595" height="485"></iframe></p>
<div style="margin-bottom: 5px;"><span style="color: #ff6600;"><strong> <a title="Stop killing your child" href="//www.slideshare.net/das_gv/stop-killing-your-child-32226384" target="_blank"><span style="color: #ff6600;">Stop killing your child</span></a>&nbsp;- a slide show&nbsp;</strong>by cyclist&nbsp;<strong><a href="//www.slideshare.net/das_gv" target="_blank"><span style="color: #ff6600;">Dasarathi GV</span></a>, that recounts his personal experience of getting affected by air pollution.<br /></strong></span></div>
<h3>&nbsp;</h3>
<h3>Very little data on health impacts</h3>
<p><strong>First, there is no data on Non Communicable Disease</strong><strong> (NCD) </strong><strong>&nbsp;trends over the years for Bengaluru. </strong></p>
<p>Neither Bruhat Bengaluru Mahanagara Palike (BBMP) nor the state government collects comprehensive NCD data.</p>
<p><strong>Second, there are very few studies on the health impacts of air pollution.</strong></p>
<p>The lack of disease registries and digitised hospital records makes such epidemiological studies more difficult, says Dr R S Dhaliwal, Scientist &lsquo;G&rsquo; &nbsp;at the NCD Division of Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR), Delhi. He says that short term studies especially, can be easily done using such data.</p>
<p><strong>Third, there are no recent studies on the specific pollutants in Bengaluru, and their sources.</strong></p>
<h3>World standards much higher than Indian ones</h3>
<p>In many Western countries, air pollution became a concern over 50-60 years back when it started to cause deaths. Since then, many countries have developed robust pollution control strategies based on research.</p>
<p>For instance, the US Environmental Protection Agency (USEPA) of the United States, conducts its own scientific studies and also gives grants to other organisations for research. Many pollutants were banned because of strong scientific studies that showed their impact on humans. For eg., research in US in the 1970s showed that CFCs (chlorofluorocarbons) were depleting the ozone layer which could lead to cancer, cataract etc in humans. Despite strong protests from industries, in 1978, US, Canada and some European countries banned the use of CFCs in aerosol spray cans.</p>
<p>When further research in the 1980s showed more severe impact of CFCs, it led to three international agreements to phase them out.</p>
<p>According to WHO&rsquo;s Global Burden of Disease Report, 6.2 lakh premature deaths occurred in India due to outdoor air pollution in 2010 alone. It said that outdoor air pollution was the fifth largest killer in India, and indoor air pollution the second.</p>
<h3>Studying Bangalore&rsquo;s pollutants</h3>
<p>Particulate matter - specifically PM<sub>10</sub> and PM<sub>2.5</sub> - is considered the most common and dangerous pollutant in India. PM, or Particulate Matters, is a mixture of many solid and liquid particles suspended in the air; its composition varies across different regions. Particles with diameter less than 10 &mu;m(micrometer, i.e., one-millionth of a meter) are called PM<sub>10</sub>, and those with diameter less than 2.5 &mu;m are called PM<sub>2.5</sub>; PM<sub>2.5</sub> is more harmful than PM<sub>10</sub>.</p>
<div class="middle-column-special-box-right">
<ul>
<li>57% increase in PM10 between 2010 and 2014</li>
<li>In 85% of location the levels have begun to exceed the standards. The worst hit pollution hotspots include Graphite India Whitefield; AMCO battery Mysore Road; Silk Board Hosur; and Victoria hospital. (CPCB data).</li>
</ul>
</div>
<p>In Bengaluru, KSPCB has 15 monitoring stations - 13 of these are manual stations that analyse data twice a week, and two are automated ones collecting continuous data. These stations measure only three parameters. Three other stations directly come under the CPCB; these monitor 21-27 parameters. Data from these three stations are used to calculate the Air Quality Index (AQI) for the city.</p>
<p>Sumit Kumar Gautam, a Fellow at TERI (The Energy and Research Institute), says that these measurements can only show if air quality is good or not. It cannot identify the specific pollutants that make up PM, and also cannot identify their sources. Without knowing this, one would not know what pollution sources to control. To get such data, source apportionment studies are needed.</p>
<h3>No action on studies done</h3>
<p>In 2007, CPCB and MoEF oversaw source apportionment studies done by different organisations for six cities, including Bengaluru. The <a href="http://www.cpcb.nic.in/Bangalore.pdf" target="_blank">Bangalore study</a> was done by TERI, and Gautam was part of the research team. The study recommended many measures like wall-to-wall paving of roads, controlling the number of vehicles, shifting from BS IV to BS VI fuel vehicles directly etc. Gautam says that hardly any of these recommendations have been implemented. &ldquo;In fact the number of vehicles have doubled since 2007.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The study had also recommended that further source apportionment studies should be done once every three years. But no study has been done since 2007 at all for Bangalore. The 2007 study itself was commissioned based on the recommendations of Mashelkar Committee Report of 2003, which had pointed out the lack of scientific data on air pollution.</p>
<p>Gautam says that such studies are needed because only a few pollution sources can actually be controlled. Source apportionment studies identify the sources of PM (road dust, vehicles etc) and the extent to which each source contribute to PM. Next, the individual pollutants emitted by each PM source is identified by chemical characterisation. For eg., road dust includes pollutants like aluminium and silica. &ldquo;Sometimes the source that contributes the most to PM may not have the worst impact. May be the source that contributes only 25% to PM has the worst carcinogens and needs to be controlled,&rdquo; says Gautam. In addition to PM, inventory of other pollutants like carbon monoxide, and their sources, are also needed.</p>
<p>He says that without knowing which sources are more harmful, we may end up controlling those that don&rsquo;t really matter, and realise it only after many years.. Such confusion was recently seen in Delhi upon implementation of odd-even vehicle policy; there were debates on whether vehicles actually contributed the most to pollution.</p>
<h3>No funds for studies!</h3>
<p>But Gautam says that TERI has had difficulty getting funds for source apportionment studies, despite being in touch with government agencies and corporates. &ldquo;Organisations like IISc and TERI have the technical capability for these studies. But such a study in Bangalore would cost around Rs 1.5 crore.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A senior officer at the CPCB South Regional Office in Bangalore opines that even if such studies are done, there is hardly any government action to reduce pollution. &ldquo;Also, CPCB&rsquo;s main role is to monitor pollution rather than research.&rdquo;</p>
<p>S Suresh, scientist in charge of CPCB South zone office in Bengaluru, says that CPCB does not have sufficient specialisation and manpower to do such studies by itself. &ldquo;Getting other organisations to do studies is a policy decision. And such decisions are made by the Member Secretary of CPCB based in Delhi.&rdquo;</p>
<p>However, conducting source apportionment studies is part of the Terms of Reference (TOR) of a newly constituted committee under the KSPCB Chairman. It has to be seen whether the new committee will actually help advance such research.</p>
<p>Gautam says that research is needed for conclusive proof to push for action. &ldquo;Earlier, big particles like those emitted by coal trains were considered dangerous. Only with advancement of science, we realised that it is actually PM<sub>10</sub> that&rsquo;s dangerous, and later that PM<sub>2.5</sub> is even more dangerous.&rdquo;</p>
<h3><strong>Health impact studies not done</strong></h3>
<p>There are many health impact studies on air pollution in developed countries, but researchers say that these studies only give a broad idea, and cannot be directly applied to India. Health impacts may differ here because the type of pollutants and the level of exposure are different.</p>
<p>For example, India&rsquo;s major pollutants like coal and diesel exhaust are not major pollutants in many developed countries; so studies done in developed countries would not capture health impacts in India. Differences in population and vehicle densities, lack of home air-conditioning also cause different health impacts. Also, in India, urban poor and some professional groups like traffic policemen have worse exposures than general population.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Differences in weather - temperature, rains etc - also lead to different health impacts. Lifestyle factors like malnourishment also have a huge role,&rdquo; says Dr George D&rsquo;Souza, Dean at St John&rsquo;s Research Institute, Koramangala. He says that genetic factors may also make a difference.</p>
<p>&ldquo;For example, Indians&rsquo; lungs are much smaller than that of Europeans. We don&rsquo;t know if it&rsquo;s a good thing or bad. Smaller lungs may mean that we are taking in lesser quantity of pollutants, but it could also mean that the surface area for absorbing pollutants is smaller and hence impact is higher.&rdquo;</p>
<p><strong><span id="docs-internal-guid-7996fda3-3862-21d4-ec2a-89e9ac8416b9" style="font-size: 14.666666666666666px; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">Does air pollution reduce birth weight?</span></strong></p>
<p>The first long-term study in India on the health impacts of air pollution started in 2010 at the Department of Environmental Health Engineering in Sri Ramachandra University, Chennai. The study, costing Rs 5 crore, was funded by ICMR. Its results are yet to be fully analysed, but a preliminary finding is that air pollution is linked with low birth weight in newborns, says Dr Guruswamy Thangavel, a member of the research team.</p>
<p>The study had continuously tracked 1200 pregnant women from urban and rural Tamil Nadu throughout their pregnancy, and thereafter assessed the newborn every month for the next two years. Researchers used medical data from hospitals, pollution data from Tamil Nadu Pollution Control Board, and measured household pollution using individual pollution monitoring stations in every woman&rsquo;s home.</p>
<p>Dr Kalpana Balakrishnan who heads the research team, advocates more such studies in India. In a <a href="http://ehp.niehs.nih.gov/wp-content/uploads/119/1/ehp.1003273.pdf" target="_blank">2011 write up</a>, she, alongwith co-authors R.S. Dhaliwal and Bela Shah, argues that at least short term studies are feasible in India as better data is available now from Pollution Control Boards (PCBs), hospitals and municipalities; short term results can be used to extrapolate long term risks. She says that there should be studies on different types of health impacts from different pollutants, unlike existing research that is almost only about poor lung function in polluted areas.</p>
<p>Dr Thangavel says that long term studies are few in India because epidemiology is a new field here and because air pollution became a concern only in the last two decades. &ldquo;Also in India, generally not much attention is given to chronic diseases like pregnancy outcomes and respiratory diseases.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Scientists say that studies help understand what policy decisions to make; but more importantly, conclusive evidence can force governments to take action. &ldquo;Research can clearly show the economic cost to the country due to air pollution. Hopefully that will prompt bodies like CPCB (Central Pollution Control Board) and MoEF (Ministry of Environment and Forests) to take action,&rdquo; says Dr Dhaliwal.</p>
</div>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A green weddingit's possible!</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/a-green-eco-friendly-wedding-in-bengaluru</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/a-green-eco-friendly-wedding-in-bengaluru</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Gadadhar Prem Kumar</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<br/>The father of the groom shares a personal account of how one can celebrate something as grand as a wedding, without creating too much of a burden on the environment.]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p>A few months ago, there was this <a href="http://www.deccanherald.com/content/516956/bride-helps-prevent-137-kg.html" target="_blank">news item</a> about a bride who prevented 137 kilos of wedding waste from ending up in a landfill. It was heartening to read it, for two reasons. One, even in these days of pomposity, show and fanfare, there are some who have genuine concern for the environment, and think about wastage, garbage and the like. The second reason for my happiness was a sense of pride, since our own family had pursued this initiative just a few weeks before.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Yes. In October 2015, we had arranged a luncheon get-together, to celebrate the wedding of my son. Every member of our family was unanimously against a &lsquo;big fat reception&rsquo;, preferring a low key, simple event. The luncheon was arranged at Woodlands, a popular, 70-year-old hotel in Bengaluru, well known for its service and cuisine.</p>
<p>We printed only 80 hard copies of the invitation card, for the benefit of those without online facility or knowledge. The printed card was also a single sheet of art paper, rolled into a scroll and tied with a ribbon &ndash; novel in appearance, and also saving on expensive and elaborate cards and associated envelopes. The rest of the invitees got their invites through e-mail or WhatsApp.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16863/pic_article_Green_wedding_invitation.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">A simple scroll in place of an opulent wedding invite. Pic: Pranav S Krishnan</p>
<p>Since Woodlands was known to serve food on plantain leaves only, the problem of using styrofoam or similar undesirable crockery did not arise. However, we had to have many discussions and parleys with the management on the subject of not using plastic in any way. This was particularly applicable to serving water in reusable tumblers, instead of in plastic/paper disposable tumblers or water bottles. Finally, they agreed to serve water in reusable tumblers, provided we supplied the same.</p>
<p>Most unexpectedly, this subject of tumblers assumed gigantic proportions, and almost became a challenge to our intentions!</p>
<p>Today, with the plastic demon reigning all over the place, it was a Herculean task to locate a source renting out said tumblers! Why would anyone run a business where there is no demand? At last, we managed to find RNR in Chamarajpet, where we could hire tumblers &ndash; steel, or what they called, fiberglass. The latter looked more &lsquo;appealing&rsquo; than the steel ones, so we hired the requisite numbers, with a big sigh of relief!</p>
<p>Alas! How true is the saying that looks are deceptive! As a result of being unused and/or not being cleaned for long, the tumblers had a fair amount of dust and muck stuck inside them &ndash; all hundreds of them! On the eve of the event, it took six of our family, all of three hours, to clean the tumblers properly, dry them to prevent more accumulation, and remove the strands of cloth fibre adhering to the frayed rims of the &lsquo;good looking&rsquo; tumblers! Crisis management at its peak!</p>
<p>The get-together went off very well. There were no ostentatious decorations to adorn the hall &ndash; few bouquets at the entrance, some colored cloth embellishment. No thermocol artwork, no plastic buntings, no plastic floral extravaganza! Whatever food was left over, the hotel gave to us, packed in containers that we had taken, with a good amount of anticipation and forethought.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16861/pic_article_Green_wedding_flower_decor.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">The entrance to the hall. Pic: Pranav S Krishnan</p>
<p>No tale is complete without a villain! Quite unobtrusively, the plastic devil had sneaked into our scheme of things, despite all our meticulous plans! Horror!</p>
<p>The attractive <em>malai</em> sandwich was kept in front of all of us in dainty plastic cups, with plastic spoons! If only we had known about this earlier, we could have hired hundreds more cups, and dedicated another three hours for cleaning them! We had to accede a small victory to our &rsquo;enemy&rsquo;, and swallow our defeat by relishing the delicious savory!</p>
<p>We do not also know how the hotel staff disposed of the used plantain leaves wrapped in the paper backing! We hope they do have a proper segregation and disposal system for the waste.</p>
<p>Instead of the usual traditional <em>tamboola</em>, we had arranged for plants to be the parting gifts. This concept was instilled in us some years ago by Gopal, my son&rsquo;s friend, during his marriage. I hope that his married life is prospering as healthily as the jasmine plant we got on the occasion is blossoming in our garden.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16862/pic_article_Green_wedding_flowers_at_wedding.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Plants were handed out as giveaways. Pic: Pranav S Krishnan</p>
<p>For our event, Indo American Hybrid Seeds supplied an assorted variety of saplings, consisting of flowering plants, and also medicinal plants like aloe vera, <em>doddapathre</em> and <em>tulasi</em>. It was gratifying to see that this initiative was an instant hit with our guests, who vied with one another for the plants of their choice! Cloth-like woven carry bags were provided to carry the plants safely.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16860/pic_article_Green_wedding_carry_bags.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">The carry bags that were given out. Pic: Pranav S Krishnan</p>
<p>Paper bags in the required size were not available easily and, and cloth bags turned out to be more expensive than the saplings. I hope there is sufficient demand for cloth bags, making them more affordable. Some of the invitees who could not attend the function even approached me later, and picked up some leftover plants from my house!</p>
<p>The advocates of &lsquo;big fat weddings&rsquo; and &lsquo;<em>Band Bajaa Baarats</em>&rsquo;&ndash;if they condescend to read this at all&ndash;may smirk and snort at our small effort! Well, all good acts have their critics, detractors and dissenters. What we had done was certainly not a big crusade, but a small beginning, a miniscule contribution.</p>
<p>I learn that a Minister&rsquo;s daughter also adopted a similar initiative during her wedding. It is very encouraging, because these are people who are taken as role models, and are expected to set examples for others to emulate. It is heartening to know that many groups, welfare associations and organisations have started tackling this issue, in their own ways.</p>
<p>If more and more people join the clarion call of &lsquo;Garbage <em>Hatao</em>&rsquo;, Swachh Bengaluru, and Swachh Bharat, will be a reality, and not just a slogan! Treatment of garbage is not a solution; prevention of garbage generation is the right cure for this malady.</p>
<p>Just as little drops of water make a mighty ocean, little lumps of litter lead to large loads of garbage!</p>
<p>We have opted to be the little drops of water. What about you?</p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The black sea of Namma Bengaluru: Bellandur lake in pictures</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/the-black-sea-of-namma-bengaluru-bellandur-lake-in-pictures</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/the-black-sea-of-namma-bengaluru-bellandur-lake-in-pictures</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2016 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Akshatha M</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<br/>Deep waters in the heart of Bellandur Lake tell the story of what is wrong with the lake and how it can be fixed. A pictorial journey into the centre of the lake.]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16822/pic_article_Bellandur_lake_23.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">A view of Bellandur lake from Sobha Lakeview Club House. Pic: Akshatha M</p>
<p>Enough has been said and heard about infamous Bellandur lake. But what does the lake spread across 800 acres actually look like? How polluted it is?</p>
<p>A team of researchers from Indian Institute of Science led by Prof T V Ramachandra and army personnel from Madras Engineering Group (MEG) have been conducting bathymetric survey of Varthur and Bellandur lakes for the last 10 days.</p>
<p>Bathymetric survey aims to study the character of water across the various layers. This will help in scientifically deciding how to restore the water quality and rejuvenate the lake. This exhaustive survey has been initiated by community groups - Whitefield Rising and Bellandur Lake Group.</p>
<p>As I cruised across the lake in a military boat piloted by soldiers from Madras Engineering Group, in the company researchers from Indian Institute of Science, here is what I came across. High rise &ldquo;Lake view&rdquo; apartments on the one side, dense green cover on the other, the water covered with hyacinth, the dirty black water all around&hellip;.Bellandur lake is much more than we know.</p>
<p>While I saw the ugly side of the lake, flocks of water birds sitting on hyacinth gave me some hope about the life that still exists in this dying lake. Indulge in the photo essay on the unseen side of one of the largest lakes in Bengaluru!</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16801/pic_article_Bellandur_lake_2.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>Green carpet on the lake? &nbsp;They are hyacinth, the troublesome aquatic weeds. Hyacinth reduce the oxygen level in water leading to suffocation of water organisms, like fish. Pic: Akshatha M</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16824/pic_article_Bellandur_lake_26.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>Highrise apartments surround one side of Bellandur Lake. These apartments command premium rates, for they offer 'lake view'. Ironically, if you live close to Bellandur lake, all you experience is unbearable stench. Pic: Akshatha M</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16805/pic_article_Bellandur_lake_5.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>While one side of the lake is covered with high rise buildings, the other side has some green pastures. This is the Defence dairy farm land. Pic: Akshatha M</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16819/pic_article_Bellandur_lake_20.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>And those beautiful birds! Some relief at last. Flocks of water birds fly above the lake. Pic: Akshatha M</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16825/pic_article_IMG_7569.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>Madras Engineering Group (MEG) on the boat. Teams from MEG and IISc have been carrying out&nbsp;the Bathymetric survey&nbsp;braving the sun and extreme heat. Pic: Akshatha M</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16810/pic_article_Bellandur_lake_10.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>Pitch black water reflects the sad state of affair of Bellandur lake. Water quality seems worse in this part of the lake which is close to the sewage inlet. Anaerobic condition is created here in the absence of free oxygen. Pic: Akshatha M</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16812/Bellandur_lake_12.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>Stinking water and bubble formation somewhere in the middle of Bellandur lake. Pic: Akshatha M</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16814/pic_article_Bellandur_lake_15.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>Bathymetric survey under progress at Bellandur lake. Researchers measure the sediment thickness and depth of the polluted lake. Pic: Akshatha M</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16816/pic_article_Bellandur_lake_17.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>Research team collects the sample of silt at Bellandur lake. Sample will be further tested to examine the chemicals and contamination in the silt. Pic: Akshatha M<br /><br /><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16817/pic_article_Bellandur_lake_18.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>Sample collected at one point during the study.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16823/pic_article_Bellandur_lake_24.JPG" alt="" /></p>
<p>IISc and MEG team that conducted the study at Bellandur Lake. A team of 13 personnel from MEG and 12 researchers from IISc are part of the Varthur and Bellandur lakes survey.</p>
<p><strong><em>All the pictures in the article are clicked by Akshatha M. Copying them in any form is prohibited. They cannot be shared without permission and credits.</em></strong></p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Citizens help kickstart scientific study of Bellandur, Varthur lakes</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/citizens-initiate-the-scientific-study-of-lakes-to-save-them</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/citizens-initiate-the-scientific-study-of-lakes-to-save-them</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2016 11:35:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Pravir B</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/14334/small_Bellandur_lake_froth__3_.jpg" /><br/><p>A small team has quietly pushed for a study to understand the issues of Bellandur and Varthur lakes, with the support of experts and army men. There is hope again that the lakes may soon see better days.</p>]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/14334/small_Bellandur_lake_froth__3_.jpg" /><p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/15459/pic_article_varthur_lake_froth_2.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">Pic: Rajesh Shah</p>
<p>Varthur and Bellandur lakes have been in the news over the past one year due to froth and fire. These lakes were last desilted in 1970. As part of the rejuvenation efforts, scientists from Indian Institute of Science (IISc) and other experts have been recommending wet dredging to remove the silt and sludge. To estimate the amount of silt and sludge that have accumulated over the years, Prof. Ramachandra of IISc recommended a bathymetric survey.</p>
<h3>IISc and MEG Teams at KK English School</h3>
<p>Citizens who took into consideration the recommendations of teh scientists seriously, joined their hands to fund the bathymetyric study, in the absence of government support. Whitefield Rising (WR) and Bellandur Lake Group requested Prof. Ramachandra and his team to help with the survey. He sought help with the necessary boats and people. After obtaining approval, Commandant of Madras Engineering Group (MEG) - an army wing - agreed to the request of Ambika Sen, Volunteer, WR, her husband Mr Sen, and Prof. Ramachandra.</p>
<p>A 13-member team of MEG reached Varthur with two boats on April 3. They set up camp at KK English School, where Mr Khan from KK English School and WR team extended hospitality to the MEG team and the five-member IISc team. This initiative would not have been possible without the support of the MEG team. The team worked undaunted by the heat and difficult situation on the ground. The team has been instrumental in Ulsoor Lake revival and maintenance.</p>
<h3>Varthur to Bellandur</h3>
<p>The survey and water sample collection commenced on April 4. The water hyacinth and weed cover made the task tough as the boats could not move far from the shore on April 5 for about 75 minutes. The scorching sun made life difficult as well with dehydration and other heat-related discomfort. The team completed the task at Varthur Lake on April 7 and moved to Bellandur Lake next day to set up camp there. The Bellandur Lake Group has been extending its hospitality to the MEG and IISc teams since then.</p>
<h3>Community Support</h3>
<p>Overwhelming response and support was seen from the residents around the Bellandur Lake in salvaging and restoring the lost glory of the lake. Shobha Community, Suncity Apartments, Genesis and Euphoria joined up for the drive to restore the lake. Apartments from Yemlur have joined to put pressure on authorities as they are victims to the famous chemical snow.</p>
<p>The community understands it is a long journey with a baby step towards the direction being the quality survey done by the MEG and IISC team. The community will extend its support to the state to salvage and restore the lake. Bellandur Lake being the largest lake in the city spread over approximately 900 acres is bed to flora and fauna and is a need of the society for ecological balance.</p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interim order of NGT on petition against plastic ban in Karnataka</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/interim-order-of-ngt-on-petition-against-plastic-ban-in-karnataka</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/interim-order-of-ngt-on-petition-against-plastic-ban-in-karnataka</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2016 09:27:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>News Desk</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16794/small_order_3.jpg" /><br/><p>National Green Tribunal's interim order issued while admitting the case against plastic ban in Karnataka</p>]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16794/small_order_3.jpg" /><p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16792/pic_article_order_1.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">&nbsp;<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16793/pic_article_order-2.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16794/pic_article_order_3.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="pic-caption">&nbsp;</p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When rescue is not an option</title>
      <link>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/when-animal-rescue-is-not-an-option</link>
      <guid>http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/articles/when-animal-rescue-is-not-an-option</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Apr 2016 10:22:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Deepa Mohan</dc:creator>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16782/small_Baby_kite_2.jpg" /><br/><p>Ever come across an injured animal or bird that you cannot help? It is at these times that one is reminded how cruel nature can be.</p>]]>
      </description>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in//uploads/picture/image/16782/small_Baby_kite_2.jpg" /><p dir="ltr">On the March 13th, we went to Arekere Reserve Forest (aka Doresanipalya) and while there, we found this baby Black Kite, badly injured, upon the ground.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16781/pic_article_Baby_kite_1.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>It was so badly off that it could not even clamber to its feet as it lay there in the grass clutter. It was heart-rending to watch the poor little one look at us with terrified, mute appeal.</p>
<p><img src="http://bangalore.citizenmatters.in/uploads/picture/image/16782/pic_article_Baby_kite_2.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>But alas! Very often, one cannot follow up on one&rsquo;s emotional impulse to intervene in wildlife... whether in urban or forest areas. In this case, the very fact that it was so immobile told me that the injury was definitely a bad one. The baby probably was thrown to the ground while struggling in the grip of two Shikras we had seen overhead; they must have predated the nest (we could not see one nearby), picked up the nestling, and flown off.</p>
<p dir="ltr">There was also the strong possibility that this was a nestling and not a fledgling; that is, it was a baby bird that had not yet arrived at the stage of learning how to fly.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The mother bird was circling overhead, and though scientists keep telling us not to ascribe human emotions to other creatures, the parent&rsquo;s concern was quite apparent.</p>
<p>But with a bird that cannot fly, for any reason, rescue is not a great option. One has to let Nature take its course, and remember that in the wild, Darwin&rsquo;s rule of 'survival of the fittest' applies.</p>
<p>We hardened our hearts and walked away. I still cannot help thinking of what might have happened to this little bird afterwards. These are the moments when Nature can be less than delightful.</p>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
